<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before Sr. Patience Ward, upon the last Sunday of his mayoralty, Anno 1681 with additions / by John Turner ...</title>
            <author>Turner, John, b. 1649 or 50.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 169 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63919</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3318A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23557</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12072929</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12072929</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53523</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63919)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53523)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 584:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before Sr. Patience Ward, upon the last Sunday of his mayoralty, Anno 1681 with additions / by John Turner ...</title>
                  <author>Turner, John, b. 1649 or 50.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 83 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Walter Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Corinthians, 1st, XIV, 40 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53523:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53523:1"/>
            <p> A SERMON Preached before S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Patience Ward, UPON THE Laſt <hi>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NDAY</hi> of His MAYORALTY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno</hi> 1681.</p>
            <p>With ADDITIONS.</p>
            <p>By <hi>John Turner,</hi> late Fellow of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s College in <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Virtus repulſae neſcia ſordidae</l>
               <l>Intaminatis fulget honoribus,</l>
               <l>Nec ſumit aut ponit ſecures</l>
               <l>Arbitrio popularis aurae.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Walter Rettilby</hi> at the Biſhop's Head in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard. 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:53523:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SUMMA PRIVILEGII.</hi> Conſtitutions and Canons Eccleſiaſtical, 1640. <hi>Artic.</hi> 8.</head>
            <p>WHereas the Preaching of order and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, according to St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s rule, doth conduce to edification, it is required that all Preachers (as well beneficed men as others) ſhall poſitively and plainly preach and inſtruct the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in their publick Sermons, twice in the year at leaſt, that the Rites and Ceremonies now eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> are lawfull and commendable, and that they the ſaid peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and others ought to conform themſelves in their practice to all the ſaid Rites and Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and that the people and others ought wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly to ſubmit themſelves unto the authority and government of the Church, as it is now eſtabliſhed under the King's Majeſty. And if any Preacher ſhall neglect or refuſe to doe according to this Canon, let him be ſuſpended by his Ordinary du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the time of his refuſal, or wilfull forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to doe thereafter.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:53523:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>I. COR. 14. 40.</bibl>
               <q>Let all things be done decently, and in order.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE unhappy breaches and differences among us in matters of Religion are at preſent the ſubject of univerſal Complaint; and though nothing be more talked of than an Union among Proteſtants againſt the common Enemies of our Liberties as we are <hi>Engliſh</hi> men, and of our Faith as we are Chriſtians; yet, if we will believe mens Actions, rather than their Words, there is nothing that ſeems leſs heartily to de deſired, or, if you will give me leave to ſpeak a little plainer, for it is not now a time to mince the matter, with more ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous Care and Induſtry to be avoided.</p>
            <p>For my part, I am not come hither to enflame thoſe differences, and, if I were, 'tis twenty to one but I ſhould loſe my Errant, for they are ſo great already that perhaps they are incapable of being encreaſed.</p>
            <p>But, if you will allow me that liberty which every man now pretends to as his birthright, that is, to ſpend my private opinion about the publick Concerns, I will put you in a way by which this bleſſed Union can onely be effected, and that is, by keeping up ſtrictly to the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline of the Church, and by <hi>doing all things decently, and in order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have, almoſt every day, many excellent Diſcourſes delivered in the Pulpit, to perſuade us to mutual Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Forbearance with one another; and indeed this is in a manner the whole deſign of Chriſtianity, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce in us thoſe calm and peaceable diſpoſitions of mind
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:53523:3"/> which are beſt fitted to make us happy in this life, and to prepare us for the bleſſedneſs of that other ſtate, whoſe very nature conſiſts in perfect Charity and perfect Peace. Wherefore Saint <hi>Paul</hi> tells us plainly, that without <hi>chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> which is the very bond of Peace, and of all vertues, all our pretences to Religion, and all our attainments in it, our proficiencie in ſpiritual knowledge, and our ſuper-errogation, if that were poſſible in good works, will ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie juſt nothing at all; <hi>though I ſpeak with the tongue of men and Angels,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>and have not charity, I am be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as ſounding braſs, or a tinckling Cymbal; and though I have the gift of prophecie, and underſtand all myſteries and all knowledge; and though I have all faith, ſo that I could remove mountains, and have not charity, I am no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing;</hi> nay, <hi>though I beſtow all my goods to feed the poor, and though I give my body to be burned, and have not charity, it profiteth me nothing.</hi> And if to the Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of St. <hi>Paul</hi> you will add the greater Authority of our Saviour himſelf, he makes reciprocal Charity and Love to be the diſtinguiſhing mark and character of his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, <hi>By this ſhall all men know that ye are my diſciples, if ye love one another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If therefore this Charity which is ſo eſſential to a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that he cannot be ſo without it; if the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of the ſpirit in the bond of peace</hi> can be preſerved under differing denominations of different Sects and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, notwithſtanding the different external forms and circumſtances of Divine Worſhip; if all or any of thoſe pious and learned Exhortations, which have been made to perſuade you to this Chriſtian temper, can have that good effect which is intended by them, notwithſtanding the various forms of Church Government, and the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of all other outward appendages and ceremonies of publick Worſhip; if we can <hi>fear God,</hi> and <hi>honour the King,</hi> and <hi>love one another,</hi> as well and as heartily in the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:53523:3"/> midſt of theſe differences, as if there were no ſuch things to be found among us, then, by my conſent, let all the Eccleſiaſtical Encloſures be laid open, and let every man worſhip God, ſo he do but worſhip him <hi>in ſpirit and in truth,</hi> and believe aright as to the fundamental Articles of the Chriſtian Faith, according to his own particular humour and fancie; becauſe by gratifying ſuch an harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, though unaccountable humour, there can no incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience follow, but by diſturbing and croſſing it there may; and therefore the ends of Religion will be better ſerved by a diverſity in Worſhip, than by an uniformity of it.</p>
            <p>But now, on the contrary, if it ſhould prove true, as it will moſt certainly, if either Experience or Reaſon can be heard amongſt us, that the onely way to Unity and Peace is by an Uniformity of Diſcipline and Obedience, as to the external circumſtances of Divine Worſhip, then this great end, being ſo neceſſary as it is for the procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring us all that Happineſs which either this World or the next can afford us, will juſtifie all the neceſſary means that can be uſed in order to the obtaining it.</p>
            <p>Wherefore Uniformity being neceſſary as a means to Peace, and yet being impracticable unleſs the Church be ſuppoſed to be inveſted with a Power of preſcribing the external modes and circumſtances of Obedience, it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows plainly, that the Church is actually inveſted with ſuch a Power, and that all its members are bound to obey its Preſcriptions.</p>
            <p>For the Topick of Experience, it is not without ſome unwillingneſs that I mention it, much leſs do I think it proper at this time and place to lay open the wounds of our late unhappy times, or preſent you with a mournfull Scene of thoſe Miſeries and Diſtractions which neither can nor ought to be remembred without Amazement and Horrour.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:53523:4"/>
            <p> But if you will, every one of you, retire into your own thoughts, and ask your ſelves the queſtion, What it was that brought thoſe dreadfull Calamities upon us, that involved three flouriſhing and powerfull Kingdoms in Bloud, and Slaughter, and Confuſion, that made the <hi>Gods to dye like men, and fall like one of the Princes;</hi> while Slaves were ſet over us to be our Maſters, and Frogs were heard croaking in the Chambers of our Kings; then you your ſelves will anſwer for me, It was the tender Conſcience diſſolved into rebellious Pretences, that car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed Order and Government before it, and overflow'd all things with a reſiſtleſs Stream; it was a Cry againſt Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, and Ceremonies and humane Inſtitutions; it was a Clamor for Liberty, againſt Will-worſhip and the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of men; it was a Spirit of Sedition, a Thirſt after Innovation, an inſatiable Humour of being diſſatisfied with all the wholeſome Eſtabliſhments of Unity and Peace; it was an Itch of new-modelling both Church and State; it was a Phariſaical Pretence to farther Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Purity and Holineſs; it was Diſcontent, and Jealouſie and godly Fear, lin'd with Hypocriſie and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimulation, that reduced our Beauty and Order into Aſhes, that laid the magnificent and comely Fabricks of the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Church and Empire, the Amazement of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and the Envy of their neighbours, equal with the ground; and, inſtead of one firm and well-compacted Buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, rais'd paper Tenements of crumbling Sects and Fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which, inſtead of being able to ſupport themſelves, betray'd us in a manner into that Security which we now enjoy.</p>
            <p>While we, forgetfull of thoſe Miſeries under which our Fathers and our ſelves have groan'd, unthankfull for thoſe Bleſſings which, under the ſhade and protection of a wiſe and happy Government we receive, ungratefull to Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, who out of that <hi>Chaos</hi> of Confuſion has
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:53523:4"/> rear'd this new world of Eſtabliſhment and Order, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleas'd with the fatneſs of the Olive, and the ſweetneſs of the Figg-tree, and quarrelling with the friendly and ſociable Vine that cheareth God and Man, are calling again for the Bramble to reign over us, and for the Thornes and Briars to protect us; or like the Iſraelites in the Wilderneſs, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited with Miracles, with Manna, and with Quailes, with the dew of Heaven, and with the fatneſs of the Earth; with liberty and eaſe and plenty; we are looking back for Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very from our old Taskmaſters in the Land of <hi>Ham,</hi> and longing for the Garlick and the Onyons of <hi>Egypt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But becauſe an inſtance taken from our late Confuſions, may but exaſperate whenit ſhould convince. Let us avoid the mention of that Crying Guilt, for which this Land of our Nativity has wept in tears of Bloud, and ſhould for ever mourn in Sack-cloth, and humble her ſelf before the Lord in Aſhes; and let us trace the footſteps of Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and ſearch the Records of the more innocent and early Ages.</p>
            <p>What was the reaſon in the <hi>Moſaick</hi> Diſpenſation, why all the external niceties of divine Worſhip, in their Feaſts, and in their Sacrifices, and in their Luſtrations were ſo carefully adjuſted, by the particular deſignation and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of God himſelf?</p>
            <p>It is true indeed, that moſt of thoſe Ceremonies were of a ſymbolicall nature, and were deſigned to ſhadow out unto the <hi>Jewes,</hi> either that purity, ſimplicity and innocence of mind which God expects from all his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers and ſervants; or elſe they were figurative and emblematicall Repreſentations of the life and death and ſufferings of the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> and of that more perfect Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation which was to be introduced into the World by him.</p>
            <p>But yet notwithſtanding, it muſt not be deny'd, that there are many Ceremonies to be found in the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:53523:5"/> which being equally commanded by God himſelf, were of equall obligation as to their performance, with any of the reſt, of which no ſuch Typicall account can be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. And therefore the reaſon of their Inſtitution can only be this, That ſince every thing muſt of neceſſity be done with ſome Ceremony, in ſome Place, or Time, or Order, or Geſture, or Manner and Circumſtance, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; it pleaſed God for the avoiding of Confuſion, and for the preſervation of an uniform and orderly way of Worſhip, which would otherwiſe be expoſed to perpetual change, diſturbance and alteration, to adjuſt and determine the particular circumſtances of thoſe indifferent matters, becauſe conſidering the perverſeneſs of ſome mens minds, and the diverſity of their ſeveral fancies and humours, ſuch changes and alterations could never happen without a conſiderable breach of Charity and Friendſhip among men; which muſt needs be a wonderfull Obſtruction as well to the intereſt of the Civil State, as to all the religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Performances and Duties, both as to their devotion in themſelves, and as to their acceptance with Almighty God.</p>
            <p>If therefore the nature of Mankind, be ſtill the ſame under the Goſpel that it was under the Law; if the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for the neceſſity of Uniformity be the ſame now that ever they were in former ages; if the method of this Uniformity be not adjuſted by God himſelf under the Goſpel, as it was under the Law; and if this Uniformity cannot be obtained unleſs the Church be inveſted with a right and power of preſcribing the terms of it; than it follows plainly, as hath been already obſerved, that the Church muſt be inveſted with ſuch a power, becauſe elſe it would want the neceſſary means of its own unity and preſervation, which every Society muſt be ſuppoſed by the Laws of nature and reaſon, to be inveſted with; and if the Church be inveſted with ſuch a power, then all its Members are under an indiſpenſable obligation to obey
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:53523:5"/> it, becauſe that Power which may be lawfully diſobey'd, is no Power at all: And this is ſufficient to vindicate the exerciſe of Eccleſiaſtical Cenſures.</p>
            <p>And if you demand further, Whether it be lawfull for the civil Sanction to interpoſe in behalf of the Church, to ſee that its Orders and Injunctions be duly and faithfully executed and obey'd, I anſwer that it is for this plain rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, becauſe the Civil Power has a right of exacting all kinds of lawfull Obedience from its ſubjects; and this obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience if it were not Lawfull, could not be enjoyned by the Church it ſelf.</p>
            <p>But beſides the expreſs proviſions of the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> it ſelf, there were alſo ſeveral pretended traditions of <hi>Moſes</hi> from Mount <hi>Sinai;</hi> there were likewiſe the deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations of their Wiſe men in controverted caſes; the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſions of the <hi>Tannaim</hi> and the <hi>Amoraim;</hi> and of the Schools of <hi>Hillel</hi> and of <hi>Schammai,</hi> the two ſo much cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated, but diſagreeing Founders of the <hi>Phariſaick</hi> Order. For which Traditions and Determinations of their famous Maſters, the <hi>Jewes</hi> had uſually as great if not greater Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration than for the Law it ſelf; and they were at length ſwell'd into ſo vaſt a bulk, that (like the Miſſals and the Rituals of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church at this day, which are ſo full of Ceremonies, burthenſom in their number, frivolous and ſuperſtitious in their uſe) they ate out the very life and heart of true Religion; as our <hi>Saviour</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in ſeveral places of his Goſpel with no leſs Juſtice than ſeverity complains.</p>
            <p>The Heathen World had alſo their Sacred Offices preſcribed by a certain Form as well before as under the Law: And the ſame is the caſe with the <hi>Mahome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan</hi> and <hi>Pagan</hi> Idolaters at this day; which Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of theirs, though for their number they be intoller<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to a devout Soul, which cannot ſuffer it's ſelf to be ſo far taken off from the more inward and ſubſtantial
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:53523:6"/> part of Religion, though in their nature they be moſtly foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, and in their uſe Superſtitious, and in their deſign Idolatrous, as being directed to a falſe object; yet as well theſe as the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Formalities do prove thus much by the common conſent of Mankind, that an Uniformity in the outward circumſtances of Divine Service, is neceſſary to the more due and ſolemn performance of Religious Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and to the publique peace and quiet of the World.</p>
            <p>What is the reaſon that at this day the <hi>French</hi> Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt the reformed Religion and its Profeſſors, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges with ſo much violence and fury, thorough all the ſpatious Territories and Dominions of that mighty Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch? Shall we think it is a Zeal for the Catholique Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, as they are pleaſed to call it, that is for a Fardle of abſur'd, ridiculous and blaſphemous Superſtitions, that inſpires ſo wiſe and powerfull a Prince, with ſo mean thoughts of Cruelty and Revenge? Shall we think he acts upon a principle of Conſcience, who has ſufficiently diſcover'd to the world by his inſatiable thirſt after Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, which cannot be purchas'd without the price of Bloud, that he has no other principle of action than that of a boundleſs appetite of Rule and Greatneſs? Shall he be thought to act upon a principle of Duty and Religion, who makes deſtructive and depopulating Wars without giving a reaſon, and violates the faith of Peace by arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Dependances and unwarrantable Claimes? Who conquers more by the peremptory Decrees of his late erected Chambers, than by the conduct of his Generals, or by the numbers, diſcipline and valour of his Armies?</p>
            <p>What therefore can be the true cauſe and motive, why he that glories in the bleſſed title of the Moſt Chriſtian King, ſhould yet notwithſtanding, perſecute Chriſtianity it ſelf? What elſe can be the true reaſon of all this Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and ſeeming Madneſs, but that he wiſely conſiders that the true way to Empire abroad, is by unity and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:53523:6"/> peace at home, <hi>that a Kingdome divided againſt it ſelf cannot ſtand;</hi> and that theſe differences of Religion, as they have done already in the experience of that Kingdome as well as ours, will ſome time or other prove the occaſions of great diſorders and commotions in the State?</p>
            <p>And ſhall we not then make uſe of the ſame wiſdome for the ſupport of Chriſtianity, which is with ſo much diligence and zeal made uſe of by others for its Extirpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? For Popery is either no Chriſtianity at all, or it is Chriſtianity wrapt up and hid in ſuch an heap of Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies and Superſtitions, that it can hardly be diſcerned.</p>
            <p>Is it worth our while to contend about Ceremonies when we are loſing the Subſtance? to ſquabble and fall out about indifferent things, when our Religion and our Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, our temporall and eternall Intereſt lye at ſtake? If the things preſcribed be indifferent and conſequently law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, why do we not ſhow that they are ſo by complying with them? If the quarrells raiſed about indifferent mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, do yet notwithſtanding riſe as high, as thoſe which are agitated between the Papiſts and us about matters of a neceſſary and unalterable nature; why do we not ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and compoſe theſe unhappy breaches, by adding Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility to Obedience, and by <hi>ſubmitting to every ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of man,</hi> ſo far as we may without any violation of the Laws of God or right reaſon?</p>
            <p>All our publique feuds and animoſities are comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in our Religious Diſputes, and if they were but once compoſed, we ſhould be an happy Nation. The King would be glorious, and his People ſecure. We ſhould be ſafe at home and formidable abroad. We ſhould be in a condition to ſuccor our Allyes, to relieve the diſtreſſed Proteſtants, to keep the ballance even betwixt our neighbour Princes, and to ſtop the progreſs of the Arms of <hi>France,</hi> which threaten to involve all <hi>Europe</hi> in Slavery and Superſtition together. Whereas now all
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:53523:7"/> we are able to do, is to give protection for a while to perſecuted Religion when it flies hither for ſhelter.</p>
            <p>But what will become of us, when the ſame torrent of Ambition, having overflown what ever ſtood in its way, ſhall at length beat upon the <hi>Brittiſh</hi> Shore? Shall we ſuffer our ſelves to be devoured by our own inteſtine Diviſions, when the Enemy from without is battering our Walls and throwing in his Bombes among us? or ſhall we not rather unite together for our common ſafety? and ſhall we not ſeverely repent that we did not ſooner do it before it was too late, that we did not take ſweet counſell together and go into the houſe of God as friends?</p>
            <p>Certainly this one conſideration, if it were but pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfully and frequently impreſs'd upon our minds, muſt needs have a wonderfull influence upon us, and muſt even fright men, and compell them by arguments both of fear and love, into a thorough Reconcilement with the beſt of Churches, before it be too late, as well out of a principle of Intereſt as Duty; for beſides the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of this World, it ought to afford matter of very ſad reflexion to us, or at leaſt to ſo many of us, as have been active either in cauſing or ſometing the Differences that are among us, that we muſt one day give a dreadfull account before the Judgment-ſeat of God, for a great part of that Bloud which has been ſpilt, and of thoſe Spoiles, Rapines and Depredations, which have been made by the ambition or injuſtice of our Neighbours. We muſt be accountable for the oppreſſion of our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted Brethren beyond the Seas; and for ought we know, if theſe deſtructive Animoſities be not ſoon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, for the removall of the Candleſtick from among our ſelves, and for the ſmall extirpation of the Proteſtant Religion.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Jewes</hi> had their Ritual, and the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> their Liturgies or ſet forms of Divine Service, the one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:53523:7"/> Chriſtianity, and the other long before Popery, were known in the World.</p>
            <p>And firſt, As to the Jewiſh Ritual, which cannot be deny'd to have been a thing of humane Inſtitution, it was ſo little diſapproved by our Saviour, or rather ſo highly approved, that he has been obſerved by <hi>Scaliger,</hi> and <hi>Bux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torf,</hi> and <hi>Camero,</hi> and <hi>Hugo Grotius,</hi> and other learned men, to have borrow'd moſt of thoſe expreſſions which he makes uſe of in the Inſtitution of the bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Body and Bloud from thence; and that Hymn which after the Celebration of that bleſſed Feaſt, he and his Diſciples went out to ſing together on the Mount of Olives, was by <hi>Paulus Burgenſis</hi> a Converted <hi>Jew</hi> and a learned Biſhop of the Chriſtian Church, and out of him by <hi>Buxtorf, Druſius,</hi> and others, conjectured to be the ſame which the <hi>Jews</hi> are uſed to call the <hi>Hallel hagadol,</hi> being a Song of Praiſe and Thankſgiving, conſiſting of ſeveral Pſalms, and uſed to be ſung in conſort at the Feaſt of the Paſſover and other ſolemn occaſions.</p>
            <p>And that God Almighty has actually approved thoſe indifferent circumſtances in Divine Worſhip which have not been of his own appointment, being either not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> or no where commanded in Scripture, and in uſe long before the Law was delivered; I will here prove by two other Inſtances, which I the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mention, becauſe they are omitted by the learned and judicious Writer of the <hi>Libertas Eccleſiaſtica;</hi> and becauſe they are no where, that I know of, taken notice of to this purpoſe.</p>
            <p>The firſt ſhall be taken from that paſſage in the Pſalms, <hi>Early in the morning will I direct my prayer un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, and will look up,</hi> in which words, the Pſalmiſt, addreſſing himſelf immediately to God Almighty, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes the Poſture in which he would poure out his Prayers before him, by looking up towards Heaven;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:53523:8"/> now, becauſe we cannot imagine he would have made this Vow of looking up to God in Prayer, if he thought it would have been diſpleaſing to him, and if, on the other hand, it can be proved that this was the general cuſtom of that Countrey in all their Prayers and Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations; then we have here an Inſtance of an indifferent Poſture in Prayer, which the general cuſtom of <hi>Judaea</hi> had by degrees brought into the authority and reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Law, which yet was no where inſtituted by any Divine Command; but that this was the general practice is plain from the <hi>Roman</hi> Authors, who tax them upon this account with worſhipping the Clouds and the Hoſt of Heaven. So <hi>Juvenal,</hi>
            </p>
            <l>
               <hi>Quidam ſortiti metuentem ſabbata patrem.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Nil praeter nubes &amp; caeli numen adorant.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And in the <hi>Catalecta</hi> of <hi>Petronius,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Judaeus licet &amp; Porcinum Numen adoret,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Et coeli ſummas advocet auriculas.</hi>
            </l>
            <p>Which places, though they be otherwiſe interpreted by Mr. <hi>Selden</hi> and other Learned men, and the reading of the latter of them queſtioned by Doctor <hi>Iſaac Voſſius,</hi> in his Notes upon <hi>Pomponius Mela,</hi> yet I conceive the firſt place dos ſufficiently vindicate the reading of the latter; and the Interpretation of Mr. <hi>Selden,</hi> inſtead of deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, will rather help and encourage that which I have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; for the reaſon why the ancient <hi>Jews</hi> called God by the name of <hi>Shamajim,</hi> or Heaven, was the ſame with that, for which they looked heaven-wards when ever they pray'd unto him, namely, becauſe they thought the more peculiar and beatifick preſence of the Divinity to be there; and this is the firſt Inſtance.</p>
            <p>The ſecond ſhall be taken from thoſe words of God to <hi>Moſes,</hi> Exod. 3. 5. <hi>Draw not nigh hither, put off thy ſhoes from off thy feet,</hi> for which he ſubjoins this reaſon,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:53523:8"/> 
               <hi>for the place whereon thou ſtandeſt is holy ground:</hi> now though it is true that. <hi>Moſes</hi> was bound upon the leaſt ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification of the Divine Pleaſure to obey it, yet this would have been no reaſon of his Obedience had there not been ſuch a cuſtome in the World before that time; which, not having the leaſt foot-ſtep of a Divine Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, was probably owing meerly to humane inſtitution, but yet we ſee was approved by God himſelf.</p>
            <p>This Cuſtome prevailed alſo under the Law; though in the Law it ſelf it be no where enjoyned, in all their ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Feaſts, as appears from this, that the <hi>Jews</hi> are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to eat the Paſſover with their ſhoes on; which would have been a needleſs Command, if in their other Feſtivals they had not uſed to put them off; which was therefore done, becauſe every meal among the <hi>Jews,</hi> but more eſpecially their ſolemn Feaſts, was in the nature of a Feaſt upon a Sacrifice, as I could prove more largely if it would not be a digreſſion; and therefore, being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout an act of religious Worſhip, they were uſed to put their ſhoes off, as the cuſtom of thoſe Countries was in like caſes.</p>
            <p>For this reaſon the <hi>Turks</hi> at this day do alwaies goe barefoot into their Moſchs: and it was a Precept of <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagoras</hi> recorded by <hi>Iamblichus,</hi> in his Life, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſacrifice and worſhip God with your ſhoes off.</hi> The <hi>Romans</hi> alſo did the ſame at their Feaſts, as is evident from ſeveral places of <hi>Martial</hi> and others. <hi>Joſhua</hi> is likewiſe commanded, by the Angel of the Lord, to doe as <hi>Moſes</hi> had done before him, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 5. 15. <hi>Looſe thy ſhoe from off thy foot, for the place whereon thou ſtandeſt is holy;</hi> and <hi>Joſhua</hi> did ſo. <hi>Marinus</hi> relates of <hi>Proclus,</hi> that he, being about to worſhip God, made uſe of this Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony in the performance of his Devotions, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:53523:9"/>
            <p> And, becauſe the Servants, as I conceive, were uſed to attend their Maſters to Divine Service, as <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Syrian</hi> was uſed to goe along with his Maſter to the Temple of <hi>Rimmon,</hi> and there to take off their ſhoes or ſandals for them; from thence is that proverbial Speech of <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> concerning our Saviour, whoſe Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner and Harbinger he was, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 27. <hi>He it is who coming after me is preferred before me, whoſe ſhoe latchet I am not worthy to unlooſe.</hi> Laſtly, in alluſion to this cuſtom is that paſſage of <hi>Juvenal,</hi> in his ſixth Satyr,</p>
            <l>—deinde adamas notiſſimus, &amp; Berenices</l>
            <l>In digito factus pretioſior; hunc dedit olim</l>
            <l>Barbarus inceſtae, dedit hunc Agrippa ſorori,</l>
            <l>Obſervant ubi feſta mero pede ſabbata reges,</l>
            <l>Et vetus indulget ſenibus clementia porcis.</l>
            <p>So that here we have two plain Inſtances of Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in matters of an indifferent nature approved by God, but commanded onely by men, for an immemorial cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom whoſe original or legiſlative ſanction cannot be tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and perhaps it never had any, but crept in by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, is as much an humane Inſtitution as a poſſitive Command, of whoſe Author we can give never ſo clear an account, as the Common Law of <hi>England,</hi> is every whit as much of humane inſtitution as the Statute; and thoſe Tenures which hold onely by Cuſtom or Preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion are to all intents and purpoſes as good as thoſe which have Deeds and Charters to produce.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, if Cuſtom may be comply'd with in theſe caſes, then ſo may any other humane Inſtitution, and if Cuſtom may not, then is it unlawfull for us to goe to our Devotions at thoſe times when our Neighbours and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-men are uſed to frequent them, becauſe this is an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition upon our Liberty, which is not ty'd up either to place or time any more than to any other indifferent circumſtance of action.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:53523:9"/>
            <p> But if the places and times of Divine Worſhip may be lawfully determined by the Authority of the Church, (and if they may not, then the Church has no power to ſee that God be worſhipped at all, for he muſt be worſhipped at ſome place or time or other,) then I ſee no reaſon why the ſame Authority may not equally ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to all other indifferent circumſtances of action.</p>
            <p>As for the uſe of Liturgies and Set-forms of Prayer in the Chriſtian Church, there is nothing more plain than that, as far as we can trace Antiquity, they have been conſtantly uſed, ſeveral of the ancient Liturgies are at this day extant among us; and the Service both of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and our's, is in a great meaſure taken from thence: nay, ſo ancient and in ſuch conſtant uſe have they alwaies been in the Chriſtian Church, that we have unqueſtionable Inſtances of them: in the Apoſtolical times themſelves, as hath been learnedly obſerved by a <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Lloyd, <hi>Biſhop of St.</hi> Aſaph.</note> Reverend Prelate of our own from <hi>Juſtin Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr,</hi> in his ſecond Apology, who calls the Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Chriſtians in his time, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Common Prayers:</hi> and from <hi>Pliny,</hi> in an Epiſtle to <hi>Trajan,</hi> very often cited by Learned men in defence of the Chriſtians of the primitive times, who, being examined by him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning their Manners and Religion, <hi>affirmabant hanc fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſe ſummam vel culpae ſuae vel erroris, quod eſſent ſoliti ſtato die ante lucem convenire: carménque Chriſto, quaſt Deo, dicere, ſécum invicem,</hi> &amp;c. The Learned Prelate, whom I have newly mentioned, underſtands this place of Verſes anſwering one another by turns, as we ſpeak the reading <hi>Pſalms;</hi> and I know not, ſaith he, how he cou'd better expreſs it. And indeed this muſt be allow'd to be a very proper, and a no leſs acute and ingenious In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation; for the <hi>Pſalms</hi> themſelves were many of them nothing elſe but Hymns of Praiſe and Thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving which were compoſed for the Service of the Temple,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:53523:10"/> and this ancient way of worſhipping God by Hymns, as well in the heathen World as among <hi>Jews</hi> and Chriſtians, is evident from the Hymns of <hi>Homer, Orpheus, Callima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus,</hi> and others among the <hi>Greeks;</hi> from Hymns of a like nature to be met with in the Interludes of the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Dramatick Poeſie, in the Odes of <hi>Horace,</hi> and in the Writings of <hi>Statius, Catullus,</hi> and others: And in alluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to this it is that the ſame <hi>Pliny</hi> ſaies, in a Complyment to <hi>Trajan, Animadverto etiam deos ipſos non tam accuratis adorantium precibus quàm innocentiâ &amp; ſanctitate laetari: gratiorémque exiſtimari qui delubris eorum puram caſtám<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que mentem quàm qui meditatum carnem intulerit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Among the Chriſtians, to be ſure, the ſinging of Pſalms and Hymns in honour of God and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and for the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual benefit and edification of one another, was alwaies looked upon as a ſpecial Duty, and we have ſeveral pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Scripture which do not onely vouch and juſtifie, but alſo enjoyn this Practice.</p>
            <p>If therefore Hymns and Pſalms, in which many are to bear their parts, cannot poſſibly be ſung but by a Form; if they muſt be compoſed before they can be ſung; if this be a true and proper exerciſe of Devotion and Divine Worſhip; if Praiſe and Thankſgiving be eſſential parts of Prayer, as is manifeſt from that Petition in our Saviour's own Form, <hi>Hallowed be thy Name;</hi> nay, if it be the moſt exalted and ſublime exerciſe of a devout mind; and if all this may be done, and in many caſes muſt be done by a Set-form; then, why may not the ſame be true of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts of Prayer? and, why may we not from hence conclude, that a Form of Prayer, as it is alwaies lawfull, ſo it is in ſome caſes neceſſary to be uſed? it is neceſſary, becauſe Pſalms and Hymns cannot be ſung without it; and it is neceſſary, becauſe in ſome caſes we are enjoyned to ſing Pſalms or Hymns by the expreſs command of Scripture.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:53523:10"/>
            <p> And here, before I paſs by farther, let me ask our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting Brethren one Queſtion, they in their Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are uſed to ſing together the Pſalms of <hi>David</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted into <hi>Engliſh</hi> Rhimes, ſome of them of one man's compoſing, and ſome of another; now, though the words of the Pſalms themſelves, eſpecially as they are in the original, were divinely inſpired, and therefore they may pretend, though it be a Form, yet it is not a Form of humane Inſtitution; yet the words of him that puts them into Meeter are not <hi>David</hi>'s words, any more than a Paraphraſe and the Text are the ſame: the ſame ſenſe may be expreſſed in different words, and thoſe different words are ſo many different forms to them that reade them; from whence it is manifeſt that they do not pray by <hi>David</hi>'s Form which was inſpired, but by the Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor's, which is of humane Inſtitution; and why then do they declaim ſo loudly againſt a Form of Prayer? Why they will tell us, the Scripture has no where enjoyned it; but I have proved the contrary, and they themſelves confute their own Pretences by their Practice.</p>
            <p>But, ſuppoſe the Scripture did not enjoyn it, what then? if we muſt neither pray with a Form nor without, unleſs the Scripture bid us doe one or the other, then we muſt not pray at all; for the Scripture does not any where command either of theſe, unleſs it be in the uſe of the <hi>Lord's Prayer;</hi> and yet at the ſame time enjoyns us to <hi>pray without ceaſing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But theſe Gentlemen, if they were half ſo good Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers as they are bad Divines, would have underſtood before now, that all Prayer is a Form, and that without a Form it is impoſſible to pray at all: for the ſenſe at the bottom of all Prayer is the ſame; it is either a devout ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment and admiration of the Divine Excellence and Perfection, or it is a thankſgiving for his Mercies, or an humbling our ſelves before him for our Sins, or
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:53523:11"/> entring into new engagements and reſolutions of a new Life, by offering up the Sacrifice of a broken and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite Heart; or laſtly, it is a deprecating thoſe Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which hang over our heads for our Sins, and an entreating his Goodneſs for thoſe Bleſſings which the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities of our nature, or the circumſtances of our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune and condition do require; and let theſe things be expreſſed with never ſo much variation of phraſe, yet it is not that variation in which the true nature of the Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er conſiſts; but it is the ſenſe which is at the bottom, which is alwaies the ſame, as a tune is the ſame, though it be pricked down by never ſuch variety of marks, and a ſentence the ſame, expreſs'd by ſeveral cyphers.</p>
            <p>It is not the words that God regards, but it is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Ardency and Devotion of the mind, which may be the ſame with a Form as without it; nay, in truth, it may be greater with a Form than it can be without it, becauſe then he that officiates, not being to ſeek for what he is to ſay, and his fancie and invention, not being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually upon the rack, his mind is the more intent and fixt upon the Object of his Devotion, and upon a ſober and conſiderate reflexion upon thoſe things which make up the entire theme and ſubject of his Prayer: he is not apt to diſhonour God, nor to expoſe himſelf and Religion to contempt by raſh and inconſiderate expreſſions uttered in the heat of a diſtempered and inconſiderate Zeal, which we find by experience, I ſpeak without reflecting upon any particular perſon, many of our non-conforming Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren doe, as well in their Prayers as Sermons, for want of duly conſidering what they have to ſay before-hand, which ſhows plainly what extream Preſumption and Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they are guilty of, when they pretend to utter ſuch contemptible ſtuff by the aſſiſtence of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>It is true indeed, there was in the firſt ages of the Church ſuch a thing as the Gift of utterance, but it was
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:53523:11"/> when men of mean parts and education were ſent forth to preach the Goſpel by our Saviour himſelf, who with out this could not have delivered themſelves as became the Embaſſadors of ſo great a King; it was at a time when the World could not be converted without Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, when the Fears of Death and Torments and Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution would have put all their natural faculties to ſilence, had they not been aſſiſted and encouraged by an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary influence of Divine Grace from above: It was at a time when they were to be carry'd before Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates and Rulers, to give an account of themſelves and of that Goſpel which they preached; and then it was neceſſary indeed, that a particular aſſiſtence of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Spirit ſhould overpower the fears of death, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move all apprehenſions of danger out of their way, and that the words which they were to ſpeak ſhould be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them and put into their mouths at that very inſtant, leſt otherwiſe, for want of ability or courage, they ſhould expoſe and betray themſelves and the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>But at this time of day there is no neceſſity of any ſuch ſupernatural aſſiſtence; and that it is not actually afforded appears partly from the experience which we have of thoſe that pretend to it, and partly from this that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> expreſly tells us, that the Gift of Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, of Tongues, and of Knowledge were in time to fail; and if they be not failed already, as well as thoſe other miraculous Powers of Healing Diſeaſes, and of Caſting out Devils, we have little or no reaſon to believe that ever they will; beſides, that the Gift of Tongues being manifeſtly ceaſed, and theſe three being mentioned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, we have abundant reaſon to conclude, that thoſe of Prophecie and Knowledge are ceaſed together with it.</p>
            <p>But after all, we have no Promiſe in Scripture, that God, though by his Spirit he will furniſh us with affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and zeal to the end of the World, will ever put the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:53523:12"/> very expreſſions into our mouths; the Spirit it ſelf <hi>hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth our infirmities,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> ſpeaking of this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry buſineſs of Prayer, but it is not with a Gift of utte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, but with Groans that cannot be uttered: let our words be what they will, ſo our hearts be but right, God is well pleaſed.</p>
            <l>Compoſitum jus fáſque animo, ſanctóſque receſſus</l>
            <l>Mentis, &amp; incoctum generoſo pectus honeſto.</l>
            <l>Haec cedo ut admoveam templis, &amp; farre litabo.</l>
            <p>It is true indeed, ſuch is the nature of ſtyle, that the ſame ſenſe clothed in different expreſſions, ſhall either extort reſpect or laughter; the reaſon is, becauſe all ſpeech is either proper or metaphorical; in proper ſpeech, where the words are the real and immediate marks of the things they expreſs, there we are affected with the ſentence according to the opinion we have of thoſe things which are contained under it; but in metaphorical, we are differently affected, as the Metaphors are taken from things of a contemptible or a ſerious and uſefull na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>Now nothing is more plain than that in religious Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, whether in Prayer or Sermon, nothing ought to be ſaid after ſuch a manner as to move laughter or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt inſtead of exciting Devotion and ſerious attention; but whether this end be more likely to be attained by an extempore or well-conſidered and premeditated Prayer, let any man of common ſenſe and underſtanding judge.</p>
            <p>And though ſuch raſh and inconſiderate expreſſions may be well enough approved where they are uttered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong people that are affected by noiſe rather than by ſober and judicious expreſſions, by a ſound and whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Form of words, yet it ought to be conſidered, one would think, how unbecoming ſuch things are to the gravity of one that pretends to teach and inſtruct the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:53523:12"/> World, or to the Majeſty of that Perſon whoſe Character he ſuſtains; what ſcandal it gives to underſtanding men, and what advantages to the proſane: and laſtly, how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuitable it is to the deſign of Religion, which is to make men happy by creating in them a calm and ſedate tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; not ſo much to move their Paſſions as to inform their Judgments, and to prepare them for Happineſs by wiſedom and inſtruction.</p>
            <p>But if there be any who, by the ſtrength of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral parts, by the quickneſs of their fancie, or the vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lubility of their tongues, by long cuſtom, or acquired habits, by art and ſtudy, by ringing the changes and by ſhuffling the ſame expreſſions at ſeveral times into a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral order and method, ſhall from thence ſeem either to themſelves or others to be poſſeſſed of this Gift of Prayer, yet they are in truth and reallity very much miſtaken, and it will appear they are ſo, in that they generally uſe theſe, whether talents or acquirements, or artifices and devices of theirs, rather in a way of oſtentation than uſe, by ſpinning out their Devotions to an unuſual length, and by endeavouring to captivate the ears and hearts of incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate people by that much ſpeaking which our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour condemns.</p>
            <p>Thus it appears plainly that a ſober and well-conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Form of Prayer is a manifeſt advantage both to the Speaker and the Hearer, and to the latter it is an advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage in a reſpect which I have not yet mentioned.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If I pray in an unknown tongue,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>my ſpirit prayeth, but my underſtanding is unfruitfull.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> c. 14. v. 14. And again, v. 16. <hi>how ſhall he that occupieth the room of the unlearned, ſay Amen.</hi> From whence it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows plainly, that in this age eſpecially, when the mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous effuſions of the Spirit are in a manner wholly cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, thoſe Prayers are the beſt to which we are beſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to ſay, Amen; but thoſe are manifeſtly Forms of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:53523:13"/> Prayer; becauſe in thoſe we goe along with the Miniſter himſelf; nay, we underſtand beforehand what it is he is about to ask, and ſo are the better prepared to joyn with him, and to ſay, Amen, heartily, devoutly and prepared<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to all his Petitions.</p>
            <p>And the ſame Chapter will likewiſe furniſh us with another argument againſt theſe extempore Effuſions, when they are truly and properly, and not onely preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dedly ſo, which is but to put a cheat upon the People; namely, that they are ſubject either to the heats of Enthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſm on the one hand, or to the coldneſs of Non plus and Drawling on the other; both of which expoſe Religion to contempt in the opinion, or at leaſt in the practice of thoſe whoſe deſign and intereſt it is to make it contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible and cheap, and ſerves to alienate the affections of much wiſer men than ever they are like to gain over to themſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If the whole Church be come together to ſpeak with Tongues, and there come in thoſe that are unlearned and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelievers, will they not ſay that ye are mad?</hi> and if the ſame or a like advantage may and will be taken from the indiſcretion of every extempore Pretender, there is the ſame reaſon why he ſhould lay by his pretences, and give way to a ſound and ſober Form of words.</p>
            <p>The truth is a premeditated and an extempore Prayer have each of them their inconveniences, the latter can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be without them; and the firſt, if it be not done by a man of ſome judgment and experience, he does uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly endeavour onely to ſhew his parts, as if his deſign were to recommend himſelf to the good opinion of God Almighty for a man of Eloquence and Wit: the preme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditated man does oftentimes talk ſo fulſomely as if his deſign were to cajole and cokes the great God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth; while the man of gifts and graces, as he thinks himſelf, does by ridiculous or raſh expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:53523:13"/> by mimical geſtures and affected alterations of his voice, by ſpeaking ſometimes ſo high as if he would prevail with him by clamor, and ſometimes ſo low as if he had a ſecret to communicate to his Maker, openly affront and abuſe him to his face and in the face of a numerous Aſſembly.</p>
            <p>But both theſe Inconveniences are happily avoided by the wiſe proviſion which the Church has made.</p>
            <p>If then the uſe of Forms of Prayer in the publick Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies of Chriſtians be not onely lawfull in it ſelf, and juſtified by the practice of all ages before the Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but alſo manifeſtly tending to Edification, and freed from very many and very great inconveniences to which extempore Addreſſes are expoſed, and therefore neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to be allow'd.</p>
            <p>And if though Forms of Prayer be neceſſary in the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, yet this or that particular Form be not, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Liturgy of all Churches and all Ages muſt be exactly the ſame.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, If no Formulary of Divine Service can be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced into the common uſe and practice of the Church but by the publick Sanction, whether ſacred, or civil, or both, then we have here a plain inſtance of a lawfull humane Impoſition in indifferent matters; for though a Form of Prayer be neceſſary, yet this or that Form is not; from whence it follows, beyond all poſſibility of contradiction, that an humane Impoſition in indifferent matters, or a Determination of thoſe indifferent things by the authority of men to one part of the indifference is not in it ſelf unlawfull, and whatſoever may be lawfully commanded is of neceſſity to be obey'd, unleſs we will renounce all obedience whatſoever.</p>
            <p>However, thus much will certainly be granted by the moſt avow'd Aſſertors of the Separation, that we have every one of us a right and power of determining our
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:53523:14"/> ſelves in thoſe indifferent matters; for otherwiſe the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of their indifference is deſtroy'd; and yet if thus much be but allow'd, they will find themſelves driven to an abſolute neceſſity, either to contradict themſeves, and to affirm contradictions in a breath, to ſay that the ſame things are and are not indifferent at the ſame time, or elſe they muſt bid adiew to their beloved Cauſe, and give ſubmiſſion to the Authority of the Church.</p>
            <p>For whatever natural Liberty men have in themſelves, when once they become members of a Society, they are ſuppoſed to give it up to the legiſlative or governing power of that Society ſo far as is neceſſary to the peace and quiet of it; for otherwiſe a Society and no Society would be exactly the ſame, that is, every man would ſtill remain his own Maſter, and at liberty to doe as much as ever he could before.</p>
            <p>For example, in that which Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> is pleaſed to call the State of Nature, when a man is not a member of a Body politick, but a diſtinct and perfectly indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent perſon by himſelf, he is naturally inveſted with a right and power of defending his perſon or his poſſeſſion by force of Arms, he may lawfully revenge his own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries, and he is the onely Judge when he is wronged or injur'd; becauſe without all this power he cannot live in the World, or continue in that Being which God and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture have given him.</p>
            <p>But if having liſted themſelves by mutual covenant and agreement into a Body politick or Commonwealth, for the mutual defence and preſervation of every particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar perſon and of the whole Society, men ſhall notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding after this aſſume the ſame liberty to themſelves of perſonal Revenges, and of being their own Judges in controverted caſes, without referring themſelves to the deciſion of the Law which is the civil Umpire betwixt man and man, it is manifeſt this Society cannot be of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:53523:14"/> long continuance, or rather ſo long as this Liberty is taken it can never be a Society properly ſo called; from whence it follows plainly, that it is neceſſary, if men will be members of a Society, that they give up this private power into the hands of the publick.</p>
            <p>If therefore the Church be a Society truly and proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo called; if it be that myſtical Body of which <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the Head; if the members of this Body cannot be knit and well compacted together without external rules of diſcipline and order, in which the very nature of a Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety conſiſts; if the publick Orders of the Church and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man's preſcribing rules to himſelf be inconſiſtent together, and if the obſerving no rule or method at all either in Divine Worſhip or civil converſation be rather like a man in <hi>Bedlam</hi> than a Deniſon of a ſober Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; if charity, good-will and love; if mutual help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs and reciprocal uſefulneſs to one another; if peace with God, and peace with men, and peace within our ſelves be the great deſign and buſineſs of the Chriſtian life; if a man cannot be at peace with God while he is at enmity with his neighbour; if a man can neither love, nor fear, nor know, nor worſhip God aright at the ſame time when his thoughts are taken up and filled with en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, uncharitableneſs, detraction and revenge; if no man can be happy in himſelf when he is diſpleas'd and angry with other men; if the controverſies raiſed about mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters confeſſedly indifferent have been, when and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they have happened, a perpetual bane and diſquiet to the Church; if they alwaies heighten mens Paſſions againſt and alienate their affections from one another; if they are alwaies attended with a diſturbance of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick peace, and have <hi>de facto</hi> proceeded to the utter ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion both of Church and State; if all theſe Animoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Contenſions would immediately ceaſe by a quiet and dutifull ſubmiſſion to the Authority of the Church;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:53523:15"/> if by giving up this Power, the Church, as a Body poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick or Society of men is actually diſſolved, a Society or Aggregate of ſeveral perſons, being no otherwiſe one, than as they ſubmit to the ſame Laws and are governed by the ſame external Rules of diſcipline and obedience; if Place and Time, notwithſtanding they be indifferent in themſelves as to this or that particular determination, yet is it neceſſary in the general that they ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined, otherwiſe there can be no publick Worſhip of God: laſtly, when men are met together in a religious Aſſembly; if every man ſhall follow his own particular fancie; if almoſt every ſingle perſon ſhall be ſeen in a different poſture; and if this be more like to make men look upon one another than to attend to the Miniſter or to mind themſelves; if it be more like to excite laughter than devotion; if it be a natural obſtruction to the ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and ſeriouſneſs of religious Worſhip; if, done by chance, it be a ſign of too great negligence and remiſneſs; and if, done on ſet purpoſe, it be a ſign of conceitedneſs and ſpiritual pride, while every man prefers his own way, and deſpiſes that of another; if it be a ground of cenſure, and may be a cauſe of uncharitableneſs, and, by degrees, of ſeparation; then is it plain, upon all theſe accounts which I have mentioned, becauſe it would be better if it were ſo, and becauſe it is neceſſary that it ſhould be ſo; becauſe the Church can neither preſerve it ſelf in reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion nor ſo much as in being, becauſe it is for its un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted and its perpetual intereſt, and becauſe it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to its preſervation, that it ſhould be inveſted with an Authority of adjuſting the moſt indifferent circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of Divine Worſhip; without which the bleſſed ends of Unity and Peace can never be obtained: I ſay, it is plain from all this, that the Church is actually inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with this Power, and that Eccleſiaſtical Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons may for the ſame reaſon determine indifferent mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:53523:15"/> for which the Civil forbid Adultery and Murther, namely, becauſe it is neceſſary to the publick Peace; which reaſon, if it be not ſufficient, the Civil Laws do all of them become immediately null and void, as being founded upon no other baſis but the conſideration of the publick good; but if it be a ſolid and ſubſtantial reaſon, I would fain know, if any of the Diſſenters be at leiſure to inform me, why it may not equally extend to defend the neceſſity, and conſequently juſtice of Eccleſiaſtical whether Laws or Cenſures.</p>
            <p>Eſpecially if we conſider that, as the caſe of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian world now ſtands, the ſame perſons, with the ſame intereſts, prejudices and paſſions are members both of the Civil and Eccleſiaſtical State; ſo that it is as impoſſible there ſhould be a diſturbance in the one, in which the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall be unconcerned, as that the ſame man ſhould be divided from himſelf; and it is every whit as clear, that either it is not lawfull to uſe all neceſſary means for the preſervation of the Civil Peace, or it is lawfull for the Church to concern her ſelf in the determination of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different matters, which Determinations and Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of hers may be lawfully confirmed and ratified by the State.</p>
            <p>If men could differ without falling-out, ſomething might be pretended in behalf of an innocent, though unbecoming Liberty, but ſince the greateſt feuds and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimoſities do ſometimes take their riſe from the ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt beginnings, ſince the religious differences are of all others the greateſt, and the moſt fatal to the publick Peace, ſince there is nothing ſo infinitely ſcrupulous as an unreaſonably tender Conſcience, and ſince there is no pretence ſo inconſiderable, from whence either indigent or ambitious men will not take occaſions to advance their ſecular deſigns under the ſpecious covert of a Concern for Liberty, or a Zeal for Religion, it behoves thoſe in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:53523:16"/> Authority, as they tender the reputation of their own wiſedom and juſtice, or the quiet of the World, to cut off all occaſions of diſturbance, by ſeeing that <hi>all things be done decently and in order,</hi> which rule of the Apoſtle's is founded upon the ſame reaſon upon which all Laws whether humane or divine are founded, and from whence alone they can and do receive their obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, namely, the common Intereſt of mankind and the particular Happineſs of private perſons; it depends upon the ſame reaſon and the ſame neceſſity, for which Injuſtice and Robbery are forbidden, or upon which Induſtry, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety and uſefull Arts are encouraged; which is nothing elſe but the conſideration of the publick Good, which if it be as plainly concerned in this as in any other caſe, this is ſufficient to defend the Authority of the Church, and to make its Sanctions in indifferent matters, ſo long as they are ſteered by principles of undoubted Intereſt, to be of perpetual force and obligation.</p>
            <p>Thoſe actions are properly ſaid to be indifferent, which may either be done or let alone without inconvenience or advantage to the publick, or to the intereſt of any private perſon; but if any prejudice or advantage will accrue, then there is a plain reaſon why they ſhould be done or omitted, and conſequently they ceaſe to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, and become neceſſary in proportion to the weight of thoſe reaſons upon which their performance or omiſſion is founded.</p>
            <p>So, for example, we will ſuppoſe it for the preſent indifferent in what poſture we ſay our Prayers in a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Congregation; yet if we ſay them at all, thus much is of abſolute neceſſity, that we ſay them in ſome poſture or other; but now if the Civil or Eccleſiaſtical Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, for the avoiding of Confuſion, and for the preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of thoſe Piques and Animoſities which frequently happen among men about things of little or no value in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:53523:16"/> themſelves, eſpecially when Religion is concerned, ſhall ordain that all men ſhall ſay their Prayers in one and the ſame poſture, and ſhall determine and aſſign what that particular poſture ſhall be; then here is a reaſon of Intereſt for the good of the World, and for the quiet of that Society of which we are members, why this po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture ſhould be uſed rather than any other; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently this poſture, though indifferent before, does now derive a neceſſity from that reaſon of State and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt upon which it's impoſition is founded.</p>
            <p>To be ſure men of common ſenſe and underſtanding, if they have but common honeſty joyned together with it, will take their meaſures of obligation as to the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs or unlawfulneſs of what is commanded, from it's deſign and tendency to promote or obſtruct the intereſt of the Publique, and the happineſs of particular Perſons; and if either the pretended or the real Scruples of any might be ſufficient to ſtop the courſe of Law againſt the common intereſt, there could be no ſuch thing as Order or Government in the World.</p>
            <p>There are many Laws enacted by the ſublime Wiſdome of the King and his three Eſtates in Parliament aſſembled, which though they be for the intereſt of the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, all things conſidered; yet they manifeſtly tend to the Prejudice of particular perſons, but yet thoſe very perſons are as much obliged by theſe Laws, as they who reap the benefit and advantage of them, becauſe the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of theſe Laws is to be taken from the fundamentall Conſtitution of all Societies, that a greater Intereſt be preferred before a leſs, and that when the publique advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage ſhall interfere with a private, the private muſt give place, becauſe otherwiſe the Society cannot be preſerved; how much more ſtrictly therefore are we obliged by thoſe Laws whoſe deſign and tendency being nothing elſe, but to keep us all at unity and peace together, are ſo
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:53523:17"/> plainly for the advantage of the Publique and of every particular Perſon?</p>
            <p>And if notwithſtanding the manifeſt Conducibleneſs of ſuch an Uniform way of Worſhip to the publique Peace, and the experience of thoſe ſad Effects which our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Differences have produced, every private man ſhall yet after this take upon him to Judge of the Reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs or Expedience of what is Enacted by his Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours, and ſhall from thence proceed upon I know not what Pretences, ridiculous in themſelves and deſtructive of the publique Wellfare, to withdraw his Obedience to their juſt Commands; he may as well take upon him an infinite and boundleſs liberty of queſtioning the Reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs and Equity of all Laws whatſoever, and either upon the ſame or more warrantable Exceptions, for the expedience of no Law can be more evident than of that which enjoyns Uniformity in Divine Worſhip, he may withdraw his Obedience from all kind of Government and Subjection whatſoever.</p>
            <p>But here it is Objected, That if there were nothing but the Civil Intereſt, or the Intereſt of this World to be conſidered, the experience of all Ages and Nations will ſufficiently demonſtrate, that an Uniformity in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous matters, is the beſt Expedient that can be thought of to ſecure the publique Peace. But alaſs! we carry ſouls and Conſciences about us, and theſe are precious things; there is an immortal Intereſt lyes at ſtake, which it would be great folly and madneſs to part with upon any temporal conſideration.</p>
            <p>But to this I anſwer firſt in the general, That the main deſign of Chriſtianity being to promote Peace and Charity in this world, as well as to procure us Eternal peace and happineſs in the next; and indeed the one in order to the other, it follows plainly that Uniformity in Religious Worſhip, as being a neceſſary means to Peace,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:53523:17"/> is in the general of Divine Inſtitution, though what the particular terms of that Uniformity ſhall be, the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture has no where preſcribed; as in truth it could not do, for a reaſon which I ſhall ſhew hereafter: it remains therefore, that the Church it ſelf be in all Ages furniſht with a right and power of preſcribing what thoſe terms ſhall be, and that all her members are obliged to a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Obſervance of them.</p>
            <p>But here, becauſe I have made ſo frequent mention of the Church, that I may avoid Ambiguity, and leave as little room as may be for Exception, before I go any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I will explain what I mean by that term, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out deſcending to too much nicety, the Church is one of theſe three things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it is the congregation of Chriſtian People diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed over the whole earth, and agreeing together in the fundamental Articles of the Chriſtian Faith, which are either expreſly, or by direct and lawfull conſequence, revealed in the Scriptures of the New Teſtament, to be of neceſſity to Salvation. And in this ſenſe it is not only unneceſſary that there ſhould be every where the ſame Rites and Ceremonies obſerved in the Church, but it is in the nature of the thing impoſſible that there ſhould, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of neceſſity the ſeveral manners, cuſtomes, and other circumſtances of ſeveral Nations, will introduce a diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of external Formalitie into Religious Worſhip, which may be done without any breach of Charity or Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip among men, becauſe there is no intereſt to be ſerved by promoting Feuds and Animoſities between them; and it will be all one to the peace and happineſs of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, what rites or uſages ſoever the <hi>Greek</hi> or <hi>Armenian</hi> Churches ſhall embrace.</p>
            <p>We do not much trouble our heads, though by reaſon of their near Neighbourhood we have ſome reaſon to do it, about the <hi>French</hi> ſaying Maſs, or adoring Reliques, or Images,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:53523:18"/> or praying for Dead, or worſhipping the Hoſt: Nay, you ſhall hardly ever ſee a man in a paſſion when he hears the Tragicall ſtories of thoſe horrible perſecutions againſt the profeſſours of the Reformed Religion; but though he may relieve and pity them, ſo far as a ſmall temporary Contribution will go, yet in truth and reality he is not much concerned; whereas at home we can make a ſhift to fall out about much ſmaller matters; the reaſon is, becauſe we are not embarked in the ſame bottom with them, and ſo being able to do neither good nor hurt by being angry or diſpleas'd, we ſcarce ever trouble our ſelves. But at home the pretences of Religion and Liberty, which are always ſtirring when ever there is any proſpect of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blique Diſorders likely to enſue upon them, will never fail to excite the ambitious, the diſcontented, and the needy, to embroyle the State out of principles either of Intereſt or Revenge, while the paſſions of men that day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly converſe together, and are engaged by intereſt, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, or duty in the reſpective parties, do but ſerve to blow the cole, and improve the ſparks of Animoſity into a flame of War.</p>
            <p>The conſequence of all which is, That there may be differences in the univerſal Church, conſiſting of many Kingdomes and Provinces without diſſention; and that all that whatever it is, which is requiſite to the <hi>unity of the Spirit in the bond of Peace,</hi> may be conſiſtent en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ough with differences in ſmaller matters, but that in the ſame Kingdome or Dominion this can never be.</p>
            <p>But <hi>ſecondly,</hi> By the Church we may underſtand a National Congregation of Chriſtian People, divided into many partitions or particular aſſemblies united together by an unity of Faith, and Diſcipline, and Eccleſiaſticall Juriſdiction; and this is that which I affirm to be neceſſary in every Kingdome or State that would avoid all occaſions of publique Tumults and Diſorders, and would be as
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:53523:18"/> happy either as themſelves can wiſh, or as Chriſtianity deſigns to make them.</p>
            <p>And therefore this is that unity which is by every Good Chriſtian, good Citizen, or good Subject, above all things which this world can afford, the moſt earneſtly to be deſired: for the obtaining of which, he is to ſubmit to every thing that ſhall be required of him, and he is to abſtain from every thing which is forbidden him; if all things conſidered, it may lawfully be done or avoided.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, In compliance with thoſe of the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall way, I am content to allow a third ſenſe of the word Church to be a particular and independent Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation governed by Laws and meaſures of its own, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging no Juriſdiction Forreign to it ſelf; and this is a Form of Church Government, which in a Chriſtian King<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome or Common-wealth, I affirm to be naturally un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull: And here there are two caſes to be conſidered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Either the whole body of the People is divided into ſuch particular and independent Congregations, or there is a nationall Eſtabliſhment from which theſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Congregations have ſeparated themſelves. The firſt of theſe is <hi>Babel in Effigie,</hi> the very Emblem and Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skip of Confuſion, ſubject to inconveniences that cannot be thought of till they are felt, and capable of ſuch infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite ſub-diviſions as will at length reduce the comely Form of Government by ſo many particular intereſts and facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons into a State of publick Hoſtility and Rapine; for the reaſon why men ſeparate from one another, is always out of ſome reall or ſome pretended diſlike, which diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes by actuall ſeparation, are ſo far from being compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that they are manifeſtly improved and heightned by it; and from hence ariſe ſo many ſeveral Intereſts as there are Sects or denominations of Parties in a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</p>
            <p>For it is natural to all men to deſire to gain Proſelytes
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:53523:19"/> to their own Opinion, for men to love themſelves and thoſe of their own way, and to think of other men, who are not enroll'd in the ſame liſt with themſelves, if not with a reall hatred, yet with a leſs eſteem and a compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative Averſation, which whenever a Ball of Intereſt is thrown between them, will be improved into all the ſad effects of the moſt deſperate Malice and Revenge.</p>
            <p>But here to make all ſure as I go along, I muſt repeat again, That by Independent Congregations, I mean, ſuch as own no Eccleſiaſticall Juriſdiction externall to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; from whence it is eaſie to perceive that every ſuch Congregation may be a new Sect and Party by it ſelf; as it was in a manner in the late Times, when the Sects were ſpawned in ſuch incredible abundance, that the Alphabet began to complain of want of Letters to furniſh ſo many different and diſagreeing Parties with names.</p>
            <p>Neither is it to be ſuppoſed that ſo many ſeveral Factions, notwithſtanding their differences in matters of Religion, ſhall yet conſpire in an uniform Obedience to the Civil Power, becauſe to be uppermoſt is that which they all deſire; and ſince the very ſame perſons are mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Commonwealth, and of a particular Sect or Party, it is ridiculous to hope that the State can ever be quiet, till all theſe parties can agree together to be of the ſame mind; which is, to make them ceaſe to be what they are.</p>
            <p>In the United Provinces, where the greateſt Liberty is given and taken of any other Territory in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian World, the peace of the publick could not be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured, if it were not for the Overballance of the <hi>Calvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſticall</hi> Party above the reſt; for the <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> as Sir <hi>William Temple</hi> in his Obſervations upon the United Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces takes notice, <hi>p.</hi> 204. <q>make up the body of the People, and are poſſeſſed of all the publick Churches
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:53523:19"/> in the Dominions of the State as well as of the onely Miniſters or Paſtours, who are maintained by the publick, who have no other Salaries than what they receive from the State, upon whom they wholly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend;</q> and for that reaſon they will be ſure to preach obedience and ſubmiſſion to the People.</p>
            <p>But yet notwithſtanding this, ſo great has the power and intereſt of the <hi>Louveſtane</hi> or <hi>Arminian</hi> Party alwaies been, that it has been the occaſion of great revolutions among them; and as it was probably one of the main cauſes of their ſo ſudden fall from the height of envy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the loweſt region of pity and deſpair within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs of a very few years, ſo it is to be feared that in not many more (the animoſities between a <hi>Calviniſt</hi> and whoever differs from him being irreconcileable and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting) it will prove the ruin of that once powerfull, but now declining State.</p>
            <p>Neither was there any thing in the late unhappy times, next to the Title of an incomparable Prince, to whom the Sceptre of theſe Kingdoms did of right belong, and the Affections of a loyal Party, which all the republi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can Cruelties were not able to extinguiſh, that contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted ſo much to put a period to the Uſurpation, which was never eſtabliſh'd upon any certain bottom, as the bandying of the ſeveral Factions againſt one another; which made it both neceſſary for the Uſurpers to ſupport their power by the Sword, and that Sword it ſelf not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all of it of the ſame metal, and the Army that was to wield it, being it ſelf canton'd into Sects and Factions, they began at length not to underſtand one anothers language, but were forced to leave working any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and to deſiſt from building that <hi>Babel</hi> of Religion, cemented with bloud inſtead of mortar, which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with the quiet of the Earth, and by which men in vain expect to climbe to Heaven.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:53523:20"/>
            <p> It is a prodigious thing for a man to conſider what ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reconcileable feuds the ſmalleſt differences in Religion have created, and ſtill the ſmaller thoſe differences are, the higher uſually are thoſe animoſities that are produced by them, as if it were the nature and <hi>genius</hi> of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind to make up in paſſion what they want in reaſon; as the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> though agreeing in all other parts of the <hi>Mahometan</hi> Superſtition, yet about a very ſmall Punctilio they are at mortal jars with one another; and, being ſo near neighbours as they are, they never want an opportunity of expreſſing their reſentments by the frequent and bloudy Wars betwixt thoſe two formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable Empires.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Calviniſts</hi> purſue the <hi>Lutherans</hi> and <hi>Arminians,</hi> who on their own parts are not wanting to retaliate the kindneſs, with every whit as great if not greater hatred than thoſe who do <hi>toto coelo errare,</hi> the <hi>Popiſh,</hi> I mean, the <hi>Mahometan</hi> and the <hi>Pagan</hi> World; nay, ſo apt are men to fall out with one another, that the moſt inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable niceties of difference that can be conceived, when they are uſed as marks of diſtinction, when men ſhall obſtinately perſiſt in ſuch diſcriminations, and when they ſhall place an opinion or affectation in them, will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce in them a diſlike and averſation for one another; and, let the difference be never ſo ſmall, yet it will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies be true to the World's end that, <hi>Birds of a feather will flock together;</hi> ſo many diſtinctions as there are, ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thoſe diſtinctions which Trade and Functions and the Neceſſities of humane life have made for the mutual ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and maintenance of each other, ſo many ſeveral Parties and Factions you ſhall have in that Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth or Kingdom where thoſe diſtinctions are found.</p>
            <p>Though in this caſe it will alwaies happen, that the ſmaller Fiſhes will aſſociate and unite together againſt the <hi>Leviathan</hi> or prevailing Party, that overballances the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:53523:20"/> reſt, but when that King of the Waters is deſtroy'd, they will then begin to prey upon one another, and contend which of them ſhall ingroſs the Dominion of the Seas, which is the caſe of all the Republican Factions againſt the Church of <hi>England</hi> at this day; though as well rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon as former ſad experience may inſtruct us, when they have obtained their end, if ever they do obtain it, which God forbid, what miſerable work they will make of it among themſelves.</p>
            <p>It is to be confeſs'd indeed that there are abroad very great heats and contentions to be found, which are not of ſuch dangerous conſequence to the publick Peace, ſuch as are thoſe feuds, which will never be extinguiſh'd, betwixt the Seculars and the Regulars, and betwixt the regular Fraternities with one another; and, I believe, there are but very few monaſtick Societies will be found that are at peace within themſelves; of which, and of the cauſes of it, which I have well conſidered, I could ſay more, if it would not be a digreſſion; but whether it be that common obedience which they pay their Holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Pope, which keeps them in ſomewhat better order, or, that being men of a ſingle life, not encumbred with any ſecular intereſt or concern, their animoſities cannot ſo eaſily embroile the State as thoſe who have a greater intereſt in it, and who may with a better coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance purſue ſecular deſigns than they can doe; or, whether it be that the Laiety think it not worth their while, any further than it is matter of common enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment and diſcourſe, to take any part in the quarrels of Beadeſmen and of Beggars; or whether it be that their contentions are not of ſuch a popular nature as to have an influence upon any but themſelves who make them; or that the perpetual auſterities of their reſpective rules, which are a conſtant emploiment to them, hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them from being capable of proſecuting any dango<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:53523:21"/> deſign, with that addreſs and diligence which is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to its ſucceſs; or that all the heat of theſe conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions is ſpent, by men that know better how to uſe their tongues than ſwords, in complaints to the Pope, and in writing againſt and cenſuring one another; or, laſtly, whether it be that their way of life in the retirement of their cloyſters, and in the little formalitie of their cells, and convents renders them unexperienc'd in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, liſtleſs and unactive in buſineſs, and unfit to doe any great good or miſchief in the World; or whatever the true reaſon be, there is no queſtion but they are found by long experience, by giving an example of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty and contentment, and by the reputation of their ſanctity and holyneſs of life to be rather an advantage than detriment to the places where they are ſuffered, and they make ſufficient amends for their inteſtine diviſions, by their being united together in the <hi>Papal</hi> Intereſt and in the ſupport of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Tyranny over the Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of men.</p>
            <p>But let the reaſon be what it will, it is certain that no reaſon can juſtifie the lawfullneſs of ſeparate and indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Congregations in a Chriſtian Commonwealth or Kingdome, which are in their own nature, and have been found ſo by experience, to be ſo deſtructive to the welfare and happineſs of the World, which are ſo big with inconveniences not to be foreſeen till they are felt, which are ſurrounded on every ſide with infinite and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable dangers, to which no poſſible remedy can be apply'd, but by the removal of their neceſſary cauſe, and by deſtroying the Independencie it ſelf, that I make no ſcruple to pronounce it as a ſelf-evident Maxim, that an aggregate of ſeparate and diſunited Congregations, unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable to one another or to any ſuperior temporal Head inveſted with a power of Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction and Cenſure, is contrary to the Law of Nature, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:53523:21"/> of the Peace of the World, and of the deſign of Chriſtianity it ſelf, which is to engage men in cloſer obligations of unity and friendſhip with one another, and therefore ought not to be tolerated in a Chriſtian State no more than Atheiſm or Infidelity themſelves; it being the extremity of Non-ſenſe and religious Folly to allow that Charity, Good will and Peace are the indiſpenſable duties of a Chriſtian; nay, the characteriſtick indications of his being <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Diſciple; that <hi>God is Love,</hi> and that <hi>whoſoever loveth not his brother whom he hath ſeen, cannot poſſibly love God whom he hath not ſeen;</hi> and yet, that that Form of Church Government is, I will not ſay of divine Inſtitution, but of divine Permiſſion, which is in its very nature and eſſential conſtitution ſo exactly fitted to bring the World into Confuſion and Diſorder.</p>
            <p>And ſo I have done with the firſt Caſe, which ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes the whole Body of a People to be parcell'd out into many diſtinct and independent Congregations. Give me leave now to ſpeak a very little to the ſecond, which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes onely a Separation of one or more Congregations from the Body of the National Church, ſetting up a new Authority of its own, and diſowning the Juriſdiction of the publick: which ſecond Caſe differs onely in propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the firſt, and will of neceſſity labour with all thoſe ill conſequences in its degree and meaſure with which the firſt is incumbred; and, it being much eaſier for ſmall things to encreaſe than to begin, the conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces at the long run will be exactly the ſame, if the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, by a wiſe temperament of Care and Courage, do not put a timely ſtop to the progreſs of ſuch ill bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding beginnings.</p>
            <p>Into ſuch ſeparate Aſſemblies as theſe all the ill humors of the Body politick will naturally flow, thither the unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate, the diſcontented, the covetous and the ambitious
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:53523:22"/> will betake themſelves, to ſeek revenge againſt reall or ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary wrongs, to repair the decaies and ruines of a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken fortune, to ſatisfie the craving circumſtances of pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and want, and to fill up the wide capacity of immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, unreaſonable and unjuſt deſires at the expence of the publick welfare, ſecurity and quiet.</p>
            <p>Neither are ſuch Conventicles as theſe dangerous one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Civil Peace, by being the natural cauſes of em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broilment and diſturbance, the very ſinks and common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhores into which all bad humors diſembogue themſelves and find a welcome entertainment, while the ſimplicity of ſome ſuffers it ſelf, under the ſpecious pretences of an extraordinary zeal, to be miſled and carry'd away cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive by the deſigning Hypocriſie of others; but, which is ſtill worſe, they have a no leſs pleaſing aſpect upon Religion it ſelf, which either by the infinite pretences to greater purity, a moſt abſurd and fooliſh cauſe of Separati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which knows no Law, and will admit no bounds, they refine ſo long till they have utterly loſt it; or by a moſt impious and unreaſonable claim to I know not what Goſpel Liberty, they get at laſt to be Libertines indeed, and are placed as far above the reach of Ordinances as thoſe Ordinances themſelves, by their deſign and uſe for the preſervation of Love and Unity in the Church, by their Divine inſtitution and appointment, and by the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernatural Grace which is exhibited and convey'd by a due and worthy participation of them, are plac'd above the blaſphemous contempt of ſuch profane and diſſolute Wretches.</p>
            <p>But I would by no means be ſo far miſunderſtood, as if I were ſo uncharitable as to think that all, or ſo much as the greateſt part of thoſe that ſeparate, doe it out of any bad deſign; for I am not onely morally certain of the contrary, as to the much greater number of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but as to the Paſtors themſelves, if that be any cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:53523:22"/> for them; I dare be confident, in very many inſtances, that <hi>the blind lead the blind,</hi> and that they are not ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of thoſe diſmal inconveniences to which their Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is naturally expoſed; but in what I have juſt now ſaid I chiefly reflect upon the ſad experience of former times, which is ſufficient to convince us, what the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine tendencie of theſe new models is; and I do no more queſtion that the ſame cauſes, if ſuffered to operate with the ſame freedom, will have the ſame effect, than I do, whether humane nature and humane paſſions be the ſame now that they were twenty or thirty years ago; which Conſideration if all well-meaning, but miſguided Chriſtians would ſeriouſly lay to heart, I cannot doubt but it would ſoon have a very wonderfull effect upon the Peace and Settlement of theſe diſtracted Kingdoms, by perſuading all that heartily wiſh the Proſperity of <hi>Sion</hi> and pray for the Peace of this our ſpiritual <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to leave their ſeparate Aſſemblies, and betake themſelves into the boſom of the Church, which cannot behold ſo much goodneſs and ſincerity ſo miſerably miſled and gon aſtray without all the concern that is natural to a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſed, forſaken Mother, and ſtands alwaies ready with her arms wide open, and with an entreating voice and mind to receive them into her moſt tender and paſſionate embraces.</p>
            <p>Some ſort of Unity as to external Diſcipline is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to the conſiſtence even of thoſe leſſer bodies; nay, the Quakers themſelves who are much the moſt exorbitant of all Parties to be found among us, yet they differ from others, and agree with one another in nothing more than in a certain Formality peculiar to themſelves: And how much more deſirable would it be, that all Parties, lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſide their reſpective heats and animoſities which under ſuch diverſity of outward forms they ſo dangerouſly foment and carry on againſt each other, ſhould unite together
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:53523:23"/> under one common rule in ſuch a bleſſed band of Peace and Love, as would remove all our Jealouſies, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent all our Fears, and make every man in the Streets in an unknown Face, to meet <hi>his Guide, his Companion, and his own familiar Friend?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is my firſt Anſwer to the Objection taken from the pretence of a Tender Conſcience, That an Unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of one ſort or other, is of abſolute neceſſity to the peace of the Church; which Uniformity ſince it cannot be obtained, unleſs men could all jump into the ſame mind of themſelves, and continue in it when they had done, it follows unavoidably that there is, and muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways be in the Church a ſtanding Authority, from whence the Sanctions of Diſcipline and Order ſhall receive their obligation.</p>
            <p>I come now to give a more particular Anſwer to the Objection propoſed, and in that, I ſhall conſider in the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral what the terms of this Uniformity muſt be, or rather what kind of terms they are to which all Chriſtian Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are obliged to ſubmit.</p>
            <p>It muſt be granted therefore, That though an Unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity in Religious Worſhip be that which is above all things in this World the moſt paſſionately to be deſired, yet this being only in order to that great End, to which all our endeavours and counſels ought to be directed, the Eternal happineſs and ſalvation of our Souls; no terms of Uniformity ought to be ſubmitted to which are incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with Salvation. And that Church, whatever ſhe is, let her pretences to Infallibility and Truth, be never ſo great, which impoſes thoſe either Opinions or Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as the terms of Communion, which are directly contrary to the word of God, or to the light of Nature and the impartial dictates of right Reaſon is by no means to be communicated with any longer; but we muſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately come out from Her and ſeparate in our own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:53523:23"/> leſt we be made partakers of Her ſins and of Her plagues; and in this caſe it is ſhe who is guilty of the Schiſm by neceſſitating a Separation, not we who ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate when we cannot avoid it.</p>
            <p>As to matter of Doctrine, I preſume there is no man who calls himſelf a Proteſtant, of what Denomination or Party ſoever he be, who will charge our Church with any damnable Errour; but on the contrary, there are many of our Diſſenting Brethren, who, when they are tax'd with the unpleaſant imputation of propagating very abſurd and very unreaſonable Opinions, are uſed to take Sanctuary in the Articles of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> of whoſe Authority, as to ſome points, they will pretend themſelves to be the only Aſſertors, with what Juſtice, I think I have in part diſcovered in ſome other Papers.</p>
            <p>As to Ceremonies there are three Reſtrictions chiefly to be conſidered, which if they be all carefully obſerved in the diſcipline of any Church, there is no manner of pretence or ground for Separation upon a Ceremonial ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count; and thoſe three Reſtrictions are theſe which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. <hi>Firſt,</hi> They muſt not be too cumberſome and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy by their number. <hi>Secondly,</hi> They muſt not be Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious in their uſe. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> They muſt not be Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous in their direction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> They muſt not be too cumberſome and heavy by their number, for this is that which eats out the very heart and root of Religion, and takes it off from being a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votional exerciſe of the mind, by turning it into outward Pomp and Show, which can neither make us better men for the future, nor appeaſe the wrath of God, or apply to us the merit and ſatisfaction of <hi>Chriſt</hi> for what is paſt.</p>
            <p>This was that of which St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> in his time complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but yet he did not think it Lawfull to make any breach or diſturbance in the Church upon this account, but rather to take this occaſion for the exerciſe of thoſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:53523:24"/> two excellent vertues of Patience and Humility, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the good time when this burthen ſhould be remov'd by the ſame regular Authoriy that had impos'd it.</p>
            <p>This was the caſe of the <hi>Moſaick</hi> Bondage, eſpecially as that Bondage was afterwards increaſed by the <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaical</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or by the traditionary Rites and U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church; and this is at this day, and was at the time of the Reformation, and for many Ages before, the caſe of the <hi>Roman</hi> Yoak; from which the Wiſdome and Piety of our Anceſtours, has with no leſs Juſtice than Neceſſity freed us, and plac'd us in that ſtate of Chriſtian Liberty, which does not conſiſt of ſuch an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emption from all Ceremonies as ſome men ſeem to deſire; which is abſurd and impoſſible in the nature of the thing it ſelf, but in the choice of ſuch as are beſt fitted to the ends for which all Ceremonies ought to be deſigned, and have the greateſt tendency to Edification.</p>
            <p>There were other cauſes upon account of the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies impoſed by the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which might be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to juſtify a Separation, of which I ſhall ſpeak in the two following Heads.</p>
            <p>And though a National or Provincial Church have a Right and Power within it ſelf of retrenching the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluities of the Ceremonial part of their Divine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, which may very well be done without any Schiſm or Separation from the body of the Church abroad, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on the one part or the other: Yet for private men to ſeparate from the National Eſtabliſhment, upon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence that the Ceremonies are too burthenſome or too many, is manifeſtly unlawfull. The reaſon is, becauſe this will be lyable to the ſame Inconveniences, to which a ſeparation upon pretence of greater Purity, is expos'd; and in both caſes, if every private man ſhall be allow'd to judge for himſelf, and to proceed to a Separation in purſuance of that judgment, ſo infinite are the humours,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:53523:24"/> the fancies, the prejudices, the perverſities of ſome men; ſo fond are they of Novelty and Change, ſo apt to controul Authority, and ſo deſirous to be govern'd only by their own Meaſures, that there can be no laſting Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment in the World, but the Diſcipline of the Church will be alwaies reeling like a Drunken Man, and driven to and fro like a Wave of the Sea, by every Capricious wind of Innovation.</p>
            <p>We will ſuppoſe for the preſent, in favour of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters, becauſe they cannot prove it, that there are too many Ceremonies in our Church, yet I preſume it will be granted that there are not above four or five, or half a dozen too many; or if you will, to make it a plump number, and to put the Objection into better ſhape, let them be half a ſcore, which I believe upon an exact computation, will go a great way in the Ceremonies of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and let all theſe be impoſed as indiſpenſable conditions of Communion: 'Tis pretty ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere I confeſs, to lay ſo great a ſtreſs upon Indifferent Matters; but yet certainly no man in his wits will ever pretend that this is ſuch an intollerable burthen, as that he muſt needs ſeparate rather than comply; but if there be any that are ſo hardy to do it, though I will not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend them for their courage, a vertue, of which in this contentious Age we have a great deal of need; yet in my opinion they deſerve rather to be ſoundly Laught at, than ſeriouſly Confuted.</p>
            <p>What hath been ſaid of the Churches Power in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenching the number of her Ceremonies, the ſame is likewiſe true as to the Ceremonies themſelves, that they may from time to time be altered and changed for others in their ſtead by the Authority of the Church, as ſhall ſeem moſt Expedient to that publique Wiſdome for the great Purpoſe of Edification; but for every private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to challenge this Right to himſelf, is unlawfull, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:53523:25"/> liable to the ſame inconveniences, with ſeparating under colour of Ceremonious Superfluities, or of purer Ordinances and purer Worſhip, which are therefore juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be ſuſpected to proceed out of a bad deſign, becauſe they never can have any end.</p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> in ſeveral places of his Epiſtles, expreſſes great tenderneſs for the infirmity of the weak Brother, but yet, if the Inſtances of ſuch his condeſcention be exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, they will be found to be of a quite different na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from thoſe which make up the pretences of our daies, as conſiſting, firſt, in the eating of things ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed to Idols, which as looking like a participation of the table of Devils, and as being expreſly prohibited by a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary Canon of the Council of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> muſt needs give very great offence and ſcandal to the Chriſtians of thoſe daies, who did not underſtand ſo well as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> did that <hi>an Idol was nothing,</hi> and that the conſideration of the Food might well enough be preſcinded from that of the Idol, and that therefore it was lawfull for one who was well grounded in the reaſon of things and might doe it without offence to any weaker than himſelf, to <hi>eat whatever was ſold in the ſhambles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From which laſt cited place of St. <hi>Paul</hi> we may obſerve a threefold difference in the practice of thoſe times as to this Affair. Firſt, There were ſome, and they the moſt perfect Chriſtians, in which number St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf was, who would make no ſcruple of eating the <hi>Idolothyta,</hi> though they knew them to be ſuch, ſo they might doe it without ſcandal to others. Secondly, There were others who could not juſtifie to themſelves the eating of ſuch food; but yet, by Saint <hi>Paul</hi>'s permiſſion, they would not be at the pains of a ſolicitous enquiry, but ſuffering them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to remain in ignorance would <hi>eat whatſoever was ſold in the ſhambles, asking no queſtion for conſcience ſake.</hi> Laſtly, There were a third ſort, more ſcrupulous
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:53523:25"/> than either of the former, who thought themſelves bound not to eat any manner of meat but what they were ſure had not been ſacrific'd to Idols, and it is to theſe eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally that Saint <hi>Paul</hi>'s condeſcention is with abundance of equity and juſtice made, becauſe their ſcruple was foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not in a Circumſtance or Ceremony onely, but in a deep ſenſe of Devotion, and in a jealouſie for the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God and Religion.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Inſtance of this Tenderneſs of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s is taken from the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Abſtinence <hi>from things ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled and from bloud,</hi> which was not onely ſtrictly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned by the Ceremonial law, but alſo continued and confirmed by the ſame temporary Edict of the <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> Synod; and what hath been ſaid of Abſtaining from Bloud, the ſame was true likewiſe of Circumciſion, which in ſome caſes was diſpenſed with even after Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion to Chriſtianity; this was the reaſon why <hi>Paul</hi> circumciſed <hi>Timothy,</hi> becauſe of the <hi>Jews</hi> in the 16th. of the <hi>Acts,</hi> and it is his advice in the firſt to the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> c. 7. v. 18. <hi>Is any man called being circumciſed? let him not become uncircumciſed: is any called in uncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion? let him not be circumciſed.</hi> And then it follows, For <hi>Circumciſion is nothing, and uncircumciſion is nothing, but the keeping of the Commandments of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is meant in this place by <hi>becoming uncircumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi> is needleſs to my purpoſe at preſent to examin and ſcarce conſiſtent with Modeſty to explain.</p>
            <p>But that which is more pertinent to my deſign at preſent to take notice of is this, that in both theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of abſtaining from Bloud and of Circumciſion, the caſe is far different from the ſcruples of our daies; ſince it was not the ſqueamiſh averſation of a Ceremonie, but an obſtinate adherence to the Ceremonial Law on which thoſe ſcruples were founded, with which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> as it were on purpoſe to ſhow
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:53523:26"/> how little an enemie he was to Ceremonies was pleaſed for the time to diſpenſe, although the retaining of thoſe two Ceremonies in the Church, purſued into thoſe conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quencies of which they were not ſenſible, did in reality include in it a Denial of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his Goſpel.</p>
            <p>For Circumciſion, what was it but the Seal of that particular Covenant which God had entred into with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> and his Poſterity? whereas now that encloſure was laid open and that partition wall was broken down; the renting of the vail in ſunder at the inſtant of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's Paſſion was to ſignifie the final abolition, antiqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and repealment of the <hi>Abrahamitical</hi> Covenant and <hi>Moſaick</hi> Law, the Holy of Holies was at that inſtant lay'd open, whereinto not onely the High-prieſt with Sacrifices once a year, but all mankind by virtue of that great propitiatory Sacrifice which was at that time offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up upon the Croſs, without any other Sacrifice of their own than that of <hi>a broken ſpirit and a contrite heart</hi> might enter and be happy; and there was now rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied a <hi>New and better Covenant, eſtabliſhed upon better Promiſes,</hi> whereinto not the <hi>Jews</hi> onely, but all men that would accept of the conditions of the Goſpel, of what ſort or quality or Nation ſoever they were, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Jew or Gentile, bond or free, Greek or Barbarian,</hi> had a free and welcome admittance; and it was in this ſenſe onely that the Promiſe was litterally fulfilled to <hi>Abraham</hi> that <hi>his ſeed ſhould be as the ſtars of heaven, and as the ſands of the ſea ſhore for number;</hi> that is, not the carnal, but the ſpiritual ſeed, which was much lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than the other; <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 6, 7, 8. <hi>For they are not all Iſrael which are of Iſrael: Neither becauſe they are the ſeed of Abraham, are they all children, but in Iſaac ſhall thy ſeed be called: That is, They which are the children of the fleſh, theſe are not the children of God: but the children of the promiſe are counted for the ſeed:</hi> And
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:53523:26"/> again, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 29. <hi>If ye be Chriſt's, then are ye Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham's ſeed, and heirs according to the promiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Abſtinence from Bloud, though it be not ſo much a <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Inſtitution, but was as old as the Creation it ſelf, and continued all along in force till our Saviour's time; yet then its obligation, together with its reaſon, was to ceaſe, the reaſon given in the Law, which was the ſame before it, being this; that God had given it upon the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, to be an attonement for the ſouls of men: it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt therefore, that when the Sacrifice and the Oblation ceaſed, as they actually did upon the ſuffering of the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> as to their efficacy and virtue, and as the Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> had long before expreſly propheſied it ſhould doe; I ſay, when the Sacrifices were no longer allowed in which this legal Abſtinence was founded, it is plain the Obligation to the Abſtinence it ſelf muſt ceaſe together with it, becauſe, <hi>ſublatâ causâ tollitur effectus:</hi> that Cauſe upon which this Abſtinence was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned being now finally antiquated and aboliſh'd, the Effect of that Cauſe, which was this Abſtinence from Bloud, muſt of neceſſity be ſuppoſed to be abrogated likewiſe.</p>
            <p>But yet, I know not how it came to paſs, not onely the converted <hi>Jews</hi> in the Apoſtolical times, but the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſtians for many Ages together did generally abſtain from Bloud, and this Abſtinence has not wanted very learned Aſſertors even in our daies, <hi>Curcelleus</hi> has written a particular <hi>Diatriba</hi> or <hi>Diſſertation, De eſu ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinis,</hi> wherein he defends this practice, with what ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs I leave others to determin, when they ſhall have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered what I have here ſaid; to which I will now adde, to ſtrengthen the Demonſtration, that that Text of Saint <hi>Paul</hi>'s which I have already cited, <hi>whatſoever is ſold in the ſhambles, that eat, asking no queſtion for conſcience ſake,</hi> may as well refer, and does as neceſſarily doe ſo,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:53523:27"/> to a permiſſion of Eating the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which we Tranſlate, <hi>things Strangled,</hi> and to the Repealment of the prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of Blood; as to the <hi>Idolothyta,</hi> or things Offered up in Sacrifice upon the Table of Idols. For they could not eat whatſoever was ſold in the Shambles, without eating many times ſuch meat as was not killed with that exquiſite Accuracy for the draining of the Blood which was peculiar to the <hi>Jews,</hi> and derived afterwards to the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> from them.</p>
            <p>A particular Inſtance of this exceeding Care and Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitude of theirs, we have 1 Sam. 14. v. 32. <hi>And the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple flew upon the Spoil, and took Sheep and Oxen and Calves, and ſlew them on the ground; and the people did eat them with the blood;</hi> that is, lying upon the ground the Blood could not ſo eaſily be drained out of the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice that was made; and beſides, the Blood flowing about them, polluted the the ground where they lay, and defiled the Skins of the Beaſts that were killed, which put the whole Animal in a ſtate of <hi>Levitical</hi> Unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and that which made the touching of Blood to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract a Defilement, was this, that by the <hi>Levitical</hi> San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, the Blood was of an Expiatory nature, and was always Offered up by the expreſs Command of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the door of the Tabernacle, as long as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſojourned in the Wilderneſs; and ſo being ſpilt by way of Expiation, it was ſuppoſed to be Defiled with the Guilt of the Owner and his Family, who were after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to partake of the Fleſh, and therefore was Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean, as all Expiatory Sacrifices were; as is manifeſt, not only from the reaſon of the thing, Expiation being a Tranſlation of Guilt, and Guilt the cauſe of Unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but alſo from the Rites of the Sin, and the Treſpaſs Offering; which in ſome caſes were by reaſon of their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs to be burnt without the Camp, and the Skins of theſe Sacrifices did not belong to the Prieſt as in ſome other caſes, becauſe they were unclean.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:53523:27"/>
            <p> Now though it is true that after the Children of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> were ſettled in the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> this Cuſtome of bringing all Animals to be ſlain at the door of the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, was omitted, and indeed was utterly Imprac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticable by reaſon of the great diſtance of many parts of <hi>Judea</hi> from the Temple and Tabernacle; yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, God did not by this loſe that Right which he had appropriated to himſelf in the Blood, but it was in the nature of a tacit or ſuppoſed Sacrifice in behalf of the Owner, and thoſe that partook with him of the Fleſh, though it were not ſprinkled by the Prieſt before the Lord, as the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> if by reaſon of Diſtance it had not been impoſſible, would have required.</p>
            <p>By this it appears how the Beaſts that were killed in this place of <hi>Samuel,</hi> came to be defiled, and unlawfull to be eaten.</p>
            <p>Let us now ſee which was the thing I firſt intended, what care was taken by <hi>Saul</hi> for the redreſs of this neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, or at leaſt to make ſome amends for it, <hi>v.</hi> 33, 34. <hi>Then they told</hi> Saul, <hi>ſaying, Behold the people ſin againſt the Lord in that they eat with the blood. And he ſaid, ye have tranſgreſſed, roul a great ſtone unto me this day. And</hi> Saul <hi>ſaid, diſperſe your ſelves among the people, and ſay unto them, bring me hither every man his Ox, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man his Sheep, and ſlay them here, and eat; and ſin not againſt the Lord in eating with the Blood: And all the people brought every man his Ox with him that night, and ſlew them there.</hi> Nay, it is probable that the Blood was alſo ſprinkled from the hands of the Prieſts; for it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows in the next Verſe. <hi>And</hi> Saul <hi>built an Altar unto the Lord, the ſame was the firſt Altar that he built unto the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the reaſon of that Command of his, of rouling a Stone to the place where the Beaſts were to be killed, was this, That they were to be laid athwart it with their
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:53523:28"/> Necks hanging down, that ſo the blood might flow with the greater freedom out of the Orifice which was made, and might fall upon the ground without defiling the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of the Animals themſelves; as I have already taken notice in another Diſcourſe upon a very different Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from this, and in another Language.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Jews</hi> continue Obſtinate to this day in a Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous abſtinence from Blood, notwithſtanding their Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple be demoliſhed, and they do not ſo much as pretend to any thing of Sacrifice till it be rebuilt; and I know a Learned <hi>Jew,</hi> with whom I had for ſome years a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular acquaintance, who was ſo ſcrupulous in this point, that he would never eat any kind of Fleſh which he had not killed himſelf.</p>
            <p>But before I paſs any further, I will take notice of one cauſe of Saint <hi>Paul</hi>'s Condeſcention, as to the buſineſs of Abſtinence from Blood, which I did not think of before. And that is, That beſides what I have ſaid of its <hi>Levitical</hi> Pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, which it ſeems they that were the Patrons of this Opinion, did not apprehend to be aboliſhed by the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling of all thoſe legall Sacrifices in and by the Sacrifice of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> they conſidered further, that God having ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated the Blood to himſelf; which Property and Right of his they did not conceive him ever to have relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſht, they looked upon it as a kind of Sacrilege to ſeed upon Blood; and therefore abſtained from it upon the ſame Pious principle, upon which they would have abſtained from Robbing of Hoſpitals or Colleges, or from Pilfering the Ornaments of Churches, and ſeizing the Revenues of the Eccleſiaſtical State; a ſort of Piety ſo neceſſary to the honour of God, and to the proſperity and happineſs of the Church, that it ought by no means to be diſcouraged, though in a miſtaken Inſtance; much more if Saint <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf foreſaw, which we cannot tell but he might, that Sacrilegious humour of the Saints
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:53523:28"/> which our times have experienced, when the Church was ſwallowed up at one Morſel, and the Kingdome at another; when all that was Sacred and Devoted to the ſervice of Almighty God, was converted to profane uſes by Thieves and Robbers in the diſguiſe of Saints; with as little reaſon as that for which <hi>Dionyſius</hi> of <hi>Syracuſe</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted <hi>Apollo</hi> of his Golden Ornaments, upon Pretence that they were too heavy and too hot for Summer, and that in Winter they would not keep him warm.</p>
            <p>We ſee therefore that it was not a bare Infirmity with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any colour or pretext of Reaſon that was diſpenſed with in theſe caſes; for ſuch Diſpenſations if they be once allowed, there can be no end but Confuſion and the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Subverſion of all manner of Government and Order. We ſee upon what reaſons and prejudices theſe Scruples were founded, and how neceſſary it was at that time to Comply with them: We ſee likewiſe that they were not matters of ſmall Weight and Moment, they were not things looked upon on both ſides to be of an indifferent nature, they were not <hi>Controverſiae de Nugis Siculis &amp; Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris Germanis, de foliis Farfari aut Naevii Butubatis, de umbrâ Aſini, aut de lanâ Caprinâ,</hi> they were not matters of meer Ceremony and Show, matters of External Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline and Form, that exerciſed the tenderneſs and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity of thoſe times. Thoſe Babes in <hi>Chriſt</hi> that were but newly initiated into the Chriſtian Faith, and had as yet taſted only the ſincere milk of the Word, without ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturing upon ſtronger meats, were yet better fed and better taught, than to quarrel about Indifferent Matters, or to Controul their Governours in things of Publique Decency and Order. But the inſtances of their Scrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſity, were founded in ſuch things as they looked upon to be in themſelves Offences of the higheſt nature againſt the expreſs Commands of God, againſt the honour of his Name, againſt the entire and incommunicable reſpect
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:53523:29"/> which is due from all Creatures both in Heaven and Earth to his Adorable Majeſty and Greatneſs, and againſt the indiſpenſable duties of natural Reaſon and Religion; in which though they were never ſo much miſtaken, yet theſe were Scruples not of ſmall Concernment, but of the higheſt Conſequence and Importance; and St. <hi>Paul</hi> did therefore comply with the Infirmity and with the miſtakes of thoſe Good Men, not barely to gratify a ſqueemiſh Fancy, which is out of love with things for no reaſon and without any end; but leſt by oppoſing Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judices ſo deeply rooted in matters of ſo extraordinary a nature as theſe were, they might be tempted to an Apoſtacy from the Chriſtian Faith, which did impoſe burthens upon them which their Conſciences, not being yet ſufficiently informed of the true extent of that liberty which <hi>Chriſt</hi> had purchas'd for them, could not poſſibly bear; for this reaſon, it was Saint <hi>Paul</hi>'s rule to <hi>become all things to all men, that he might ſave the more;</hi> and he deſpenſed with them in ſome caſes out of meer neceſſity, that his Brother, <hi>for whom Chriſt dyed,</hi> might not be deſtroyed, by Relapſing to <hi>Judaiſm</hi> on the one hand, or <hi>Idolatry</hi> on the other: As our Learned Mr. <hi>Thorndike,</hi> and out of him the Accurate and Induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Doctor <hi>Falkner,</hi> have obſerved. And this latter caſe of Idolatry was therefore the more tenderly to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded, becauſe the Authour to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> ſpeaking of this very buſineſs, tells us, <hi>c.</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 4, 5, 6. <hi>It is impoſſible for thoſe who were once enlightned, and have taſted of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Gift, and were made partakers of the Holy Ghoſt, and have taſted the good word of God, and the powers of the World to come, if they ſhall fall away to renew them again unto repentance, ſeeing they Crucify to themſelves the Son of God afreſh, and put him to an open ſhame.</hi> And St. <hi>John</hi> in his firſt Epiſtle <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 16. tells us <hi>there is a ſin unto death: I do not ſay that he,</hi> that is our Brother, <hi>ſhall</hi>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:53523:29"/> 
               <hi>pray for it;</hi> that is, there is great danger that his Prayers will never be heard in behalf of ſuch a perſon; and what that Sin is he afterwards explains <hi>v.</hi> 21. <hi>Little Children keep your ſelves from Idols.</hi> And this is likewiſe very ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the practice of the Church in the Primitive times, who upon any ſuch Relapſe to Idolatry, were not uſed to receive the Apoſtate, though giving all imaginable demonſtrations of Repentance, into the boſom of that Church, which he had forſaken, by Sacramental Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, ſometimes at the very inſtant of Death, and ſometimes not till then; as is manifeſt from the caſe of <hi>Serapio,</hi> and others.</p>
            <p>However, ſince Peace is the thing above all others, the moſt to be prized and valued, and with the greateſt paſſion and earneſtneſs to be deſired; ſince no kind of diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline or external Form is any further neceſſary or ſo much as lawful than it ſhall be found to Contribute to this bleſſed end, ſince Rites and Ceremonies eſtabliſht in the Church, are in themſelves of a changeable nature, and ſince our Church her ſelf hath openly and expreſly declar'd, that ſhe is no longer deſirous to retain all or any of them than they ſhall be found expedient for Edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; I ſhould not be againſt cloſing with any Propoſition, let it be almoſt what it will, by which a laſting Peace and Settlement might be obtained.</p>
            <p>And becauſe I think there are but three ways to be thought of in order to this end. The <hi>firſt</hi> of which is a Toleration of thoſe that differ from us in their ſeveral differences and diſtinctions. The <hi>ſecond,</hi> an Alteration of thoſe Cuſtoms and Uſages which are excepted againſt for others in their ſtead. And the <hi>third,</hi> an Abatement or Abolition of thoſe Ceremonies which are ſcrupled without any Reparation by the Subſtitution of others in their room: Therefore I ſhall ſpeak very briefly to each of theſe particulars.</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:53523:30"/>
            <p> And firſt, A Toleration as it is commonly underſtood, is a Liberty from the Government for every man to ſay and do as he pleaſes in Religious matters for Conſcience ſake; or upon account of a tender Conſcience which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſubmit it ſelf to the publique Rule; and ſuch a Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration as this is, I affirm to be directly and poſitively un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull, becauſe it cuts the ſinews of Government in pieces, and lets the Rains looſe to all manner of miſrule and diſorder: For the truth of which I need only appeal to the Experience of former times, when by ſuch an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded Toleration, the Kingdome was put into ſuch a floating and uncertain Poſture, that we had almoſt as many alterations in Government, as there were Sects and Parties that were to obey.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> when time was, having ſhaken off the Epiſcopal Yoak, as they were pleaſed, if not to think, yet at leaſt to pretend it to be; were as much for Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity as other men, and urged the very ſame Arguments with great Judgment and Reaſon, againſt the Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency, which may now with irreſiſtable Force be retort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon themſelves; as the Moſt Reverend and Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parably Learned, the Excellent Dean of Saint <hi>Pauls,</hi> a ſingular Ornament and ſtrong Support of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church and State againſt their Enemies of both kinds, hath very Wiſely, and like himſelf, Obſerved.</p>
            <p>Nay, to what exceſs of Riot a Toleration in its ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Latitude will proceed, the extravagancies either in Opinion or Practice, or both, of the <hi>Antinomians,</hi> the <hi>Seekers,</hi> the <hi>Quakers,</hi> the <hi>Ranters,</hi> the <hi>Sweet-Singers,</hi> and the <hi>Family of Love,</hi> are a ſufficient witneſs; moſt of whoſe Opinions as they proceed only from Ignorance, or Melancholy, or a worſe cauſe, a Life ill ſpent, or a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to ſpend it amiſs for the future; ſo the Debaucheries and the Obſcenities of ſome of theſe Sects which I have named, under a pretence of I know not what Liberty,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:53523:30"/> are ſo great and ſo horrid, that I ſhould not have belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it, if I had received it from any other information than that of ſome who pretended with abundance of aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeveration, and in a Company not eaſily to be impoſed upon to ſpeak their own certain knowledge, and who, I have great reaſon to believe, would not goe about to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive either me or any other man whatſoever.</p>
            <p>Or if it be thought too grating to reflect with ſo great, and, which is ſtill worſe, ſo juſt and ſo deſerved a Severity upon the Miſcarriages of our own Age, upon Religious Pretences; you may then conſult the Annals of Antiquity; and then <hi>Epiphanius</hi> and <hi>Irenaeus</hi> will tell you, if you conſult them, that there was no Crime ſo horrid, nor any unnatural Beaſtlineſs ſo deteſtable to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature, not yet corrupted and depraved by vitious habits, which the <hi>Gnoſticks,</hi> the <hi>Baſilidians,</hi> and the <hi>Valentinians</hi> did not practiſe; the inſtances of their exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable turpitude being ſo horrid and ſo filthy, that I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member when I firſt read them, which I did in the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borious Annals of the moſt learned Cardinal and Jeſuite, <hi>Caeſar Baronius,</hi> I could not believe he had quoted his Authours aright; and when upon a more narrow ſearch into the buſineſs I found he had not deceived me, I was amazed, and could ſcarce believe my own eyes, and to this day am very loth to believe, for the reſpect I bear to Mankind, that they are true.</p>
            <p>But if ſuch Exorbitances in our Age, or any other, be the effects of Liberty, whether tolerated by others, or aſſumed upon what Pretences ſoever to our ſelves, then certainly, ſince humane Nature is alwaies the ſame, and being allow'd the ſame ſcope, will alwaies be guilty of the ſame or like Enormities, which, by the prevalence of bad example, and by the addition of impunity to tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation will alwaies increaſe, inſtead of taking up with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a dutifull compaſs of Sobriety and Moderation, ſuch
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:53523:31"/> an unbounded Liberty as this ought alwaies, by the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Severity of publick Juſtice, to be repreſs'd, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, and reſtrained.</p>
            <p>Neither muſt we be ſo vain to pretend, becauſe ſuch Enormities are not now uſually practiſed among thoſe that pretend to an higher degree of Saintſhip than their Neighbours, that therefore they never will; for we muſt not take our meaſures from the preſent ſtate of things, but we are to conſider what would follow upon the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of the Government, to which theſe ſeparate Congregations have a clear and a natural tendency in themſelves, and then we will ſuppoſe, if you pleaſe, that ſuch Libertines as theſe, if upon ſuch infinite Pretences they do not ſeparate themſelves, ſhall be expelled the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Congregations to which they belong; but there being no publick Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction, who ſhall hinder them from aſſociating into a Confederacy with one another? to which all that live as if there were no God, or have a deſire to live as if there were no Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in the World will immediately unite them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and betake themſelves thither for Protection, as to a Sanctuary of Liberty and Riot.</p>
            <p>To ſay that ſuch things will never happen is as much as to ſay they never did; for whatever has been may be again, when humane Nature which is alwaies the ſame ſhall be joyned to the ſame unhappy circumſtances of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs.</p>
            <p>To ſay that theſe things, though they ſhould hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, will never be of any dangerous conſequence to the publick, becauſe the common Intereſt of Mankind will alwaies keep a prevailing Party in better order, is to ſet bounds to a bad example, and to the corruption of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners which is impoſſible; and beſides, to proceed upon this preſumption, without taking that courſe which is in its own nature the beſt fitted to prevent any ſuch pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:53523:31"/> miſchief, which can onely be done by a regular and orderly Diſcipline, is to lean ſo much upon humane pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babilities and upon our ſelves, that it is an high provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to Almighty God to withdraw his Grace, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which it is impoſſible for any of us to perſevere in a conſtant and ſteady courſe of Vertue.</p>
            <p>But we will ſuppoſe for once, let what Toleration will be granted, that things will never proceed to this extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity; but it is ſtill to be conſidered that all theſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate Congregations are <hi>Imperium in Imperio,</hi> there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a manner ſo many ſeveral Societies as there are ſeveral and independent Congregations, without any foreign Appeal, or Judge in Eccleſiaſtical matters; for at this rate it ſhall be at the Liberty of every private Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtour to preach what Doctrine he pleaſes, be it never ſo much to the diſturbance of the Government of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, as ſome of them doe at this time take a moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardonable liberty in their Sermons: But if it be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for the Government to aſſume to it ſelf a Judgment of what Doctrines tend moſt to the Eſtabliſhment of its peace and ſafety, it is much more lawfull for it to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern it ſelf in matters of Diſcipline, which are not in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of ſo great moment, and which notwithſtanding being left undetermin'd will have the ſame effects; which it is for the intereſt of the World they ſhould be adjuſted after an uniform manner, and in which the Goſpel has left no rule, whereby we are to manage and govern our ſelves.</p>
            <p>If the Government where we live ſhall impoſe ſuch things upon our Belief and Practice as are inconſiſtent with Salvation, contrary to the duties of natural and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed Religion, and repugnant to ſuch Propoſitions of Belief as are expreſly revealed in the Scriptures of the <hi>New Teſtament;</hi> then all we have to doe is, to ſuffer pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, as our glorious Predeceſſors, the Apoſtles and the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:53523:32"/> primitive Chriſtians did, and we ſhall certainly have our reward in Heaven for ſo doing; but if we ſuffer one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for breaking the Rules of decency and order, which have been found by experience to be ſo neceſſary to the publick Peace, and which have no other tendencie, meaning or deſign, but in order to this end, unleſs we can alledge reaſonably what I ſhall by and by inſiſt upon, that there is Superſtition or Idolatry involved in our obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, this is not Perſecution but Puniſhment, we ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer either like Fools or Madmen, or, what is worſe than either of theſe, like <hi>Boutefeus,</hi> Incendiaries and Diſturbers of the quiet of mankind, and muſt not expect either the Title or the Reward of Confeſſours or Martyrs.</p>
            <p>I reckon there are three Cauſes eſpecially of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Non-conformity from the eſtabliſhed Diſcipline of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Firſt is, The Ambition, or Neceſſity, or Diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of ſome bad men who know very well what Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages may be made for the promotion of any ill De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns by a Separation; neither is it any matter whether ſuch perſons be all of them actually liſted in ſome ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Aſſembly, ſo they do but abet and favour thoſe that are; but rather by paying a perſonal obedience to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Church, which they would have not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd, but enlarged, by breaking down that Wall of partition to which we have no right, becauſe the Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters have built it upon their own ground, by endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to let in the <hi>Trojan</hi> Horſe of Fanaticiſm through the Breaches of the Church, by very ſpecious, but very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive and pernicious Pretences of moderation and comprehenſion, and ſuch other hard names, which can onely be underſtood by being felt; by a pretended ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs of diſ-uniting Proteſtants, and yet at the ſame time uncharitably repreſenting the beſt Defenders of the Reformation under the odious and invidious Characters
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:53523:32"/> of <hi>Papiſts</hi> or <hi>Popiſhly affected;</hi> by queſtioning the Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of the Biſhops in temporal cauſes, that by that means they may weaken their Eccleſiaſtical Power, by ſtriking at the King through the ſides of his loyal and well-affected Clergy; and by doing all this and a great deal more out of a diſſembled Zeal for Unity and Peace, and out of a paſſionate Concern for the Honour and Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the King and Church, they doe abundantly more miſchief than either the Diſſenters themſelves, or they who are the moſt unmanageable and indiſcreet in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of a bitter and unchriſtian Animoſity againſt them; becauſe theſe, as being prejudiced and profeſs'd Parties, will not be heard ſo equally on both ſides.</p>
            <p>Secondly, a ſecond Cauſe, though indeed in the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of cauſality it may well enough deſerve the firſt place, of the Continuance of ſuch an unnatural Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion among us, notwithſtanding there is ſo little or rather nothing at all to be ſaid in juſtification of ſo prejudicial and ſo unwarrantable a Practice, is the Neceſſity or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge of thoſe who at the happy revolution of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's return, like <hi>the riſing of the Sun, with healing in his wings to heal the Sores</hi> of three divided Kingdoms, being ejected in great numbers out of thoſe Livings and Benefices of which they were then poſſeſſed, being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <hi>to digg,</hi> unleſs it were in the Vineyard, and being <hi>aſhamed to begg;</hi> being deſirous to reak their Revenge upon the Government, which had ejected them one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for that reaſon, becauſe it could not truſt them, and becauſe they would not obey it; being tainted with the Leaven of the <hi>good old Cauſe;</hi> being ſoundly ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned with <hi>Democratical</hi> and <hi>Demagogical</hi> Principles of which it is very hard for a thorough Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth's man, eſpecially when he is no Philoſopher, to rid himſelf; being in ſome ſmall hopes, as drowning men are when they catch at a Reed, of reaping a new
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:53523:33"/> Harveſt out of the Church-lands and out of the Spoils of the Crown; being encouraged and abetted by men of like Principles and Practices and Circumſtances with themſelves, by good old Officers that had been in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, by Proprietours that had loſt thoſe Tenements and Hereditaments that never were their own, by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderate Women that are naturally fond of Saintſhip and Perſecution, by Men that were Bigots to a Party, or Dependents upon an Intereſt, that wanted a Wife, or would oblige a Chapman, or inſinuate themſelves into a Laſt Will and Teſtament; by the Womens careſſing their Husbands, and the Husbands perſuading their Wives; by cauſes that cannot be juſtifi'd, and cauſes that muſt not be named, the black Fraternity of the ſhort robe were at length ſo far emboldened, as, notwithſtanding the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity of thoſe wholeſome Laws, whoſe edge was rebated by the fatal Clemency of a too Gracious Prince, towards men that ought not to be truſted, and cannot be obliged, to own and juſtifie a Separation, which is now grown to that exceſſive height, that the Contention is no longer about Liberty, but Dominion; they break the Laws o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly, without regard to Juſtice or to Shame, and to propagate a Succeſſion of Law-breakers like themſelves, they have ordained an Under-wood of Non-conforming Shrubs, who will in time grow up to be Cedars of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, and come by the Prieſthood much by the ſame right and title that <hi>Oliver</hi> came by the Protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tourſhip, or <hi>Trincalo</hi> by his Dukedom: So that it is now with the Diſſenters as it was with the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in <hi>Jero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam</hi>'s time, they have their ſeparate Aſſemblies and their diſtinct Altars, their Prieſts, not of the <hi>Levitical</hi> or <hi>Aaronical</hi> Tribe, much leſs of the more perfect <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedecian</hi> Order, but of the dreggs and refuſe of the People, and Calves in abundance, the Idols of the Fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as far as from <hi>Dan</hi> to <hi>Bethel.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:53523:33"/>
            <p> But Thirdly, a third Cauſe of that dangerous Non-conformity which prevails among us is, a certain ſort of Opiniatrity, or Affectation, or Newfangleneſs which in all Ages uſually poſſeſſes the ordinary ſort of People, by which they are alwaies apt to quarrel an find fault with the preſent Eſtabliſhment, let it be never ſo wholeſome; and if it were not for this Cauſe, the other two Cauſes which I have mentioned would want a ſubject upon which to work: but certainly, if men would ſeriouſly conſider with themſelves how dangerous all Innovations in the general are, and how deſtructive oftentimes to the publick Peace; how little moſt of them are like to get by Innovation, and how much they may loſe; how ſmall and inconſiderable, how unreaſonable and unwarrantable the preſent Differences are; how neceſſary it is there ſhould be ſome Eſtabliſhment, and how impoſſible that any ſhould pleaſe all; and that this is but to perpetuate quarrels by the nicety of ſome and the deſign of others, from one generation to another without any meaſure, moderation or end, to the inexpreſſible and unconceivable diſturbance of the World; they would not then think it worth their while to loſe the Quiet of their own minds, their Charity for others, and the good opinion of others for them, to crumble into Sects and Parties, to embroil us in infinite and inextricable Difficulties at home, and to expoſe us to the unavoidable Dangers of a foreign yoak, and a foreign Religion from abroad; onely to gratifie the Deſigns of proud, or diſcontented, or neceſſitous men; to feed Contempt and Ignorance themſelves, and to cloath Want of loyalty, learning, good nature and good manners.</p>
            <p>It is true indeed, that the Wiſdome of this World is Fooliſhneſs with God, and that the Wiſdome of God is Fooliſhneſs with this World, and that they are oppoſite the one to the other; but then by the Wiſdome of this
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:53523:34"/> World, is meant, that Carnal Mind that hath a greater conſideration for a Temporal Intereſt, than for the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of Truth and Vertue; for the Commands of God, or the precepts of the Goſpel; but that men that have little or no Learning of their own, and yet are unaſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by thoſe extraordinary helps of Utterance and Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Illumination with which the <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> times were furniſhed; men that are ſo far from underſtanding what Reaſon is, that they decry it; men that are ſteered wholly by conſiderations of Intereſt, by impulſes of Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by an habit of Prejudice and a principle of Revenge; that theſe of all others ſhould be thought the fitteſt to Inſtruct the People, and to have the care and conduct of ſuch precious things as are the Souls of men committed to their Charge; that theſe ſhould be thought worthy to be the inſtruments of our Confuſion, who have nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the wit nor the honeſty to make us Happy, who deſign us no Good, and can do us none if they did deſign it; is a thing which I am very confident, will find no manner of countenance from Scripture, and is utterly unable to plead the leaſt ſhadow of a Grant or Commiſſion from above.</p>
            <p>An unlimitted Toleration muſt of neceſſity be unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, if any thing be; becauſe it contradicts the deſign for which all Laws are made, and that is nothing elſe but to ſecure the Peace and Quiet of the World; which muſt needs be very inconſiſtent with an unlimitted To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration, by which nothing elſe is or can be meant, but a Liberty for every man to doe or ſay as he pleaſes, ſo he doe it upon a Religious account, or out of a Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Conſcience, of which himſelf is the only judge in this caſe: to ſay otherwiſe, being to conſtitute ſuch a foreign Appeal, is altogether incompetible with ſuch a toleration.</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:53523:34"/>
            <p> Now if it can be proved that the allowance of ſeparate and independent Congregations, without any Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in Eccleſiaſtical affairs, Foreign to themſelves, is ſuch an unlimitted Toleration in it ſelf, and will prove ſo in its Effects; then I ſuppoſe it will be granted, that all ſuch Separate Aſſemblies are unlawfull; and conſequently, that a Toleration of them cannot be allowed by the Chief Magiſtrate, or by the Legiſlative Power, without a Diſſolution of the Government, and a betraying of that Truſt which is repos'd in them for the preſervation of the publique Peace.</p>
            <p>What if an <hi>Holder-forth</hi> in a Separate Aſſembly, ſhall teach his Auditours that they owe no ſubjection to any Earthly Prince, that Rebellion is expreſly diſpenſed with in the Charter of the Saints; that Adultery, and Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege, and Theft, and Murther, themſelves; though in the Wicked and the Unregenerate, they be horrid crimes; yet they are a part of the privilege of the Elect, that all ſorts of ſwearing are in the Reprobate unlawfull; but that Perjury it ſelf, in ſuch as are ſanctifi'd and made Partakers of that new Birth by which ſo many Monſters are brought into the World, may be not only Lawfull, but Pious and Commendable, and in ſome caſes an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenſable Duty?</p>
            <p>Shall the Government in this Caſe, Shall Civil or Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Juriſdiction be allow'd to Interpoſe, by pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing ſuch Profligate and ſuch Inſolent Wretches, and by forbidding under ſevere Penalties the venting of any ſuch Doctrines for the future, which tend ſo manifeſtly to withdraw his Majeſty's leige People from their Obedience, and to the unſpeakable perill and hazard of their immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Souls? If thus much be not allow'd, then all things muſt run to Confuſion; and if it be, then if the regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of Diſcipline be found by experience to be as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to the publique Well-fare, to the peace of the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:53523:35"/> Kingdome, and to the preſervation of Charity and Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip among men; without which it is hardly poſſible there ſhould be any ſuch thing as true and acceptable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: then certainly it does as much belong to, and is as neceſſary a part of Civil and Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as the other.</p>
            <p>I know but two things that can poſſibly be urged againſt the irreſiſtible force of ſo plain a Demonſtration: I call it a Demonſtration, becauſe it will prove ſo when thoſe Objections are conſidered. <hi>Firſt,</hi> It may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended that there is no danger, ſuch Doctrines will ever be preached. And <hi>ſecondly,</hi> That a Difference grounded meerly upon matters of Diſcipline, will never produce thoſe bad Effects that are pretended.</p>
            <p>In anſwer to the <hi>firſt,</hi> there are but two things to be ſaid, the firſt is an Argument from Reaſon, the ſecond from Experience. Reaſon tells us, and ſo does Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence too, for they cannot well be ſeparated in this caſe, that men are naturally ſubject to ſeek excuſes firſt to palliate, and then arguments to defend thoſe Vices to which they find themſelves addicted, and of which they are known to be ſcandalouſly guilty, or which they would practiſe for the future without controul.</p>
            <p>The Drunkard, he puts his exceſs to the account of his friendſhip and good nature; the Luſtfull plead a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual inclination as a natural call to enjoyment; the Covetous man is deſirous of the character of Provident and Frugal; and the Ambitious would be thought a man of a lofty and heroique mind; but nothing is ſo great a plea for Libertiniſm and Licentiouſneſs of all ſorts what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, as when it is made an Inſtance of Chriſtian Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and a Freedom from the Yoak of Ordinances; to which none but <hi>Jews</hi> and Formaliſts, and the tame Vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals of the dead Letter are ſubject.</p>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:53523:35"/>
            <p> There is no queſtion to be made, but there are very bad People to be found in all Parties, let the Pretences to Religion be what they will; but it is not my buſineſs at preſent to upbraid any with their ſinfull practices, ſo they do not own the Principles from whence thoſe prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tices proceed.</p>
            <p>But what ſhall we think of the <hi>Gnoſticks</hi> of old time, that made adulterous and inceſtuous mixtures, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcuous coitions a part of their Religion? or, of the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of Love,</hi> that doe the ſame? or, of the <hi>Sweet ſingers,</hi> that drink Ale and puff <hi>Tobacco</hi> to exceſs in their very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Aſſemblies? or, of the <hi>Reformers</hi> of this laſt Age, that <hi>thought they did God good ſervice</hi> by robbing his Church and perſecuting his Servants to death, and baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and confiſcation of goods? or, of the received Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xim of thoſe bleſſed times, <hi>Dominium fundatur in gratia,</hi> that is, <hi>The longeſt Sword has the beſt Title?</hi> or, of the <hi>Fifth monarchiſts</hi> of <hi>England?</hi> of the incredible Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Villanie of the religious <hi>Incendiaries</hi> in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land?</hi> of the <hi>Zealots</hi> among the <hi>Jews,</hi> the exact Patterns of the <hi>Zealots</hi> of our daies, of whom <hi>Joſephus</hi> relates ſuch prodigious Stories? of <hi>Theudas</hi> or <hi>Theodoſius</hi> and his Followers, and of <hi>Judas</hi> of <hi>Galilee</hi> or <hi>Judas Gauloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> and his Accomplices, in <hi>the Acts of the Apoſtles?</hi> all which, under ſeveral religious Pretences, have in time paſt, or doe at preſent endeavour to ſet up for themſelves, and ſhake off the Yoak of obedience to their lawfull Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours, to their leige Lords and rightfull Maſters. What ſort of People in the World are ſo arbitrary as theſe, who yet are the loudeſt Declamours not onely againſt Arbitrary Power, but againſt all Power but their own? The <hi>Papiſts</hi> themſelves are not more bloudy than they, nor any of the perſecuting <hi>Emperours</hi> more power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully acted and poſſeſs'd by a Spirit of bitterneſs and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution. To conclude; Did not the <hi>Levellers</hi> preach
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:53523:36"/> Community of goods, according to the primitive example, (though the reaſon of that practice be now utterly ceas'd) and to reduce the natural ſtate of things, when all things lay in common, before either Induſtry or Arts began? and what is this but a more religious method of Picking of Pockets and Breaking open Houſes and Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing upon the High-way? What was it but a new Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoſe pilfering Saints, to give Thieves and Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, like themſelves, a right to the glorious Title and Reward of Martyrdom?</p>
            <p>Now if all theſe Miſchiefs and Inconveniences are ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perfectly to ſeparate Congregations, and to mens em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bodying themſelves into particular Eccleſiaſtical Societies diſtinct from the publick Diſcipline and Rule; if ſuch O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions and Practices cannot better be promoted than by independent methods, nor otherwiſe or at leaſt better be prevented than by an uniform and regular Diſcipline of the Church; then is it abundantly manifeſt that ſuch ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate Congregations, as tending plainly to the diſturbance of the World, are unlawfull; that they may, and that they ought to be ſuppreſſed; and that all the Favourers and Abettors of ſuch unlawfull Aſſemblies, are Promoters, Aiders, Comforters and Aſſiſters of Rebellion and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience both againſt God and Man.</p>
            <p>Neither is it at all material in this caſe, that many of thoſe who frequent theſe ſeparate Aſſemblies, nay, to give them their due, the infinitely greateſt part of them, are not conſcious to themſelves of any ſuch bad Deſign, but they doe it onely out of a religious prejudice which they have conceived againſt the Eſtabliſhment of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and out of an opinion which they have of the greater Sanctity of their Teachers, and Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of thoſe Ordinances of which they are made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers by their miniſtration, out of a real and an hearty zeal for God, although that zeal be not according to
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:53523:36"/> knowledge, yet we are not to conſider ſo much what it is they deſign, as what the natural tendencie of all Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration is, which, becauſe by experience it is found to bring ſo great and ſo horrid inconveniences and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs upon the World, unleſs it be timely reſtrained, it may, and it muſt of neceſſity have very bad effects; and this is enough to make men guilty of the conſequences of their Separation, though at firſt they did not intend them. He that commits a fault through want of conſideration is not altogether ſo guilty as he that knowing it to be a fault, does yet notwithſtanding commit it on ſet pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; but yet he is guilty in his proportion and degree as well as the other, becauſe it was his duty to conſider better, and ſtill the more eaſie it is too for a man to inform himſelf: (and what is or can be more manifeſt than the Prejudice ariſing from mens embodying them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into particular and independent Societies?) So much the greater is the guilt ariſing from the want of due heed and conſideration, becauſe a very little attention would have ſerved the turne, when there is ſo much rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the thing, and ſo much experience to improve that reaſon into all the certainty of demonſtration.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, It will be ſaid, That a bare difference in the externals of Religion, in matters of meer Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline and Ceremonie, will not produce thoſe bad effects that are pretended; and I wiſh with all my heart, that there were as much truth in this Exception as they that make it would have it ſeem to have; but, by Experience, which is the great Judge in this Controverſie, to which we muſt apply our ſelves for the diſcovery of the truth, the contrary does but too manifeſtly appear. For what is it that has been the true ſource and fountain of all our publick Calamities, that has made ſo dreadfull and ſo terrible Convulſions both in Church and State, but an over-heated zeal againſt Ceremonies and publick Order,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:53523:37"/> which ſort of zeal, if it be tolerated, the ſtrength and beauty of the Church is loſt, by every man's purſuing fancies of his own, or ſiding with a new modell of a particular Party inſtead of joining in the regular and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form Worſhip of the publick, which is at once an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of our Obedience to the Divine and Humane Laws, and a certain expedient of Unity and Peace with one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother; but if this zeal, inſtead of being tolerated, ſhall be reſtrained and oppoſed, then it immediately complains of Perſecution, and would have its ſufferings thought as meritorious for raiſing unreaſonable, inſatiable and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Scruples, as if the Cauſe of Chriſtianity it ſelf were at ſtake, as if it were the being of a God or the immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality of the Souls of men that were deny'd by us, and aſſerted onely by the Diſſenters from the publick Order and Rule.</p>
            <p>So that either way the inconvenience is in a manner equal, a Toleration has a manifeſt tendencie to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of the Government both in Church and State, and in that, there is no queſtion to be made, but it will certainly end, when once it has been ſuffered to have its full ſcope and ſwinge; and yet a vigorous Proſecution of the Laws againſt the Diſturbers of the Peace is branded with the odious name of Perſecution, and they that ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer by it, for being Incendiaries, are termed Saints; and becauſe it is natural for a diſtreſſed Cauſe to find a friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and pity from the common People whether it be reaſonable or no, Suffering being a very ſenſible and a very affecting thing when the Cauſes of thoſe Sufferings are not ſo plain and obvious to every common under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, eſpecially when blinded by prejudice or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern for the perſons of thoſe that ſuffer; from hence it comes to paſs that a juſt and neceſſary Proſecution of the Laws, if it be not managed with abundance of temper and prudence, ſo as it may appear it is not done out of
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:53523:37"/> hatred to a Party, but out of a real tenderneſs to the common good, may ſometimes prove the occaſion of great and fatal diſorders in a State, and may in its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence be attended with all thoſe confuſions to which a boundleſs Toleration is expoſed.</p>
            <p>This was the great reaſon of the revolt of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces</hi> from under the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Yoak; who, if they had been treated with leſs ſeverity, might probably by gentler methods have been reduced to Obedience; but by the Cruelty of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Governours and Souldiery who purſued them, eſpecially under the Government of the Duke <hi>D' Alva,</hi> with all the ſymptoms of the moſt mortal hatred, they were ſo far alienated in their affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from a Government that uſed them ſo ill, they had ſuch a dread of thoſe unheard of Cruelties and ſuch a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved averſation for that Religion that delights to propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate it ſelf by Bloud, that, being aſſiſted by the <hi>Hugo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nots</hi> from <hi>France,</hi> whoſe intereſt it was to ſtand by the Reformation, and by Supplies from <hi>England,</hi> which was glad at that time to find an opportunity to reduce the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> greatneſs to a juſter ballance with the reſt of the <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ropean</hi> Princes, they were at length perfectly ſevered from the body of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Empire, and united in a common Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance among themſelves, for the mutual ſupport and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of each other; which, though it gave begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the moſt powerfull Republick that has ever ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared ſince the <hi>Roman,</hi> yet, as a Republick in its na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and conſtitution is more expoſed to the ambition or animoſitie of bad men than a Kingdom or Monarchie is or can well be, ſo in the midſt of its greatneſs, it alwaies carried in its bowells the undoubted ſymptoms and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of its ruine, which it is to be feared, what with the Factions at home, and the daily encreaſing Power of its enemies from abroad, is not far off at this time.</p>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:53523:38"/>
            <p> But yet though Cruelty be that for which all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, but they that exerciſe it upon others, have a juſt and mortal averſation, yet a Proſecution of all Penal Laws cannot be called Cruelty, unleſs it be Cruelty to govern, or to uſe the neceſſary and the onely means to keep the World in order; all Puniſhment is Cruelty, or at leaſt Injuſtice, which is inflicted in defence of a bad cauſe or a bad religion, but when the Penalties them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeves are not ſo ſevere as to deſerve the name of Cruel, and when they are inflicted for the Preſervation of a ſound and orthodox Religion, which I perſuade my ſelf moſt of the Diſſenters will acknowledge that of the Church of <hi>England</hi> to be; when they are inflicted for the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Unity and Friendſhip among men, when this is the onely Expedient by which an univerſal Friendſhip and Charity can be maintained, by which the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can be rendred ſafe in it ſelf and eaſie to thoſe that are to obey, by which we can be rendred quiet and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure at home, or conſiderable abroad, by which we can be put in the beſt capacity to reſiſt an Enemy or to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour an Ally, or to tranſmit the Profeſſion of the Goſpel in its native purity and beauty down to our own Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and to their poſterity through all generations as long as time ſhall endure, whereas without this courſe we ſhall be ſubject to infinite changes and viciſſitudes in our Secular and in our Eccleſiaſtical Concerns, and ſhall be more dangerouſly expoſed, when our ſtrength by a Toleration is diſunited and broken in pieces, to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſions of Idolatry, Superſtition, Infidelity, Debauche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Prophaneneſs, and of all manner of Evil whatſoever it be; this is ſufficient to juſtifie a lawfull Power in the uſe of the onely means by which theſe Inconveniences may be avoided, and if it ſhall ſo happen, through the evil diſpoſition of men, that a Proſecution of the Laws, which is the onely poſſible expedient of Peace and Safety,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:53523:38"/> ſhall yet notwithſtanding produce the ſame miſchiefs and diſorders which a Toleration would have done, yet in this caſe the Magiſtrate will have the ſatisfaction in his own Conſcience and before God of having diſcharged his duty, and of not having betray'd that truſt which is repoſed in him; which in the other, as being a natural means to bring us all to confuſion, I do not ſee how he can ever have or expect.</p>
            <p>The Contentions about matters of Diſcipline are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore manifeſtly of the higheſt importance, becauſe they occaſion a Separation, which is the fruitfull mother of all thoſe fatal miſchiefs both to Church and Kingdom that have been mentioned already, and can never be too of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten repeated, or too ſeriouſly reflected upon.</p>
            <p>I would very willingly know of our Diſſenters what they think themſelves, upon ſuppoſition that the whole Nation were divided and parcell'd out into ſeparate and independent Congregations, which is that which an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limited Toleration would produce, whether or no its ſtrength wou'd be ſo firm and ſo compacted as it is now? To ſay it would, is to ſay that a divided intereſt can be as ſtrong as that whoſe parts are never ſo well compac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and knit to one another; and it is, beſides this abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the reaſon of the thing, to contradict the experience of our own Age and of all that have gone before it; to maintain the lawfulneſs of ſuch ſeparate Congregations, notwithſtanding thoſe many and diſmal inconveniences to which they are expoſed, is to affirm, that it is lawfull to endeavour the ſubverſion of the Government, which in this caſe will never be able to maintain it ſelf with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a ſtanding Army, no more than in the times of uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation; and it will be very hard, if not impoſſible; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides other incommodities and preſſures to which this way of adminiſtration is expoſed: that inſtead of deſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Laws, they ſhall not at ſome time or other ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:53523:39"/> them, inſtead of making the Prince happy and his People ſecure, they ſhall not make both miſerable, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious and dependent; inſtead of agreeing together for the maintenance of the common peace and ſafety, they ſhall not fall out among themſelves, partaking of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidemical giddineſs of the People whom they pretend to ſerve, but are in reality their abſolute Lords and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and burn up all the fences of Property and Right in the unnatural flames of an inteſtine War.</p>
            <p>I demand farther, whether they can or do ſuppoſe, though God be thanked we are not yet brought to the utmoſt perfection of Tumult and Diſorder, that the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parating of ſo many particular Congregations is not a weakning of the Government, as well as the dividing the whole Nation into ſuch independent Aſſemblies would be a ſubvertion of it? Certainly this depends in its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion upon the ſame reaſon with the other, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot be deny'd; beſides, that the preſent poſture of affairs doth ſufficiently prove it to be true, when our Heats and Diſſentions about indifferent matters, as men are pleaſed to call them, have made us, from a Nation that was uſed to be the Umpire and the Arbiter of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> to become ſo inconſiderable as we are abroad, and ſo uneaſie and unſafe at home; beſides, that by our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions we encreaſe thoſe dangers of <hi>Popery</hi> which we pretend to dread; while by an univerſal, but deſerved cry againſt ſo deteſtable a Superſtition, we are heaping coals of fire upon our own heads againſt the day of wrath and perſecution if ever it prevail among us, and we provoke our Enemies with more zeal than prudence, unleſs we would join together, as we ought to do, in a common League to reſiſt them: ſo that it ſtill appears more and more evident, upon all conſiderations, that Uniformity is neceſſary to the publick ſafety; it is neceſſary to the honour and ſeemly appearance of the Government as well
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:53523:39"/> as to the happineſs of it: it appears likewiſe that ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and independent Congregations are therefore unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, becauſe where there is no common juriſdiction there can be no common rule of diſcipline and order: it appears that a Toleration of ſuch independent Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, is a Toleration of uncharitableneſs and ſtriſe among men, and therefore as being directly and diametrically oppoſite to the very nature and temper of Chriſtianity, it muſt of neceſſity be unlawfull: laſtly it appears that humane impoſitions are lawfull, becauſe this Unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, which is ſo neceſſary to the quiet of the World and to the making Chriſtianity uſefull to ſo good an end can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not poſſibly be obtained without them.</p>
            <p>Separation, let it be for what cauſe or upon what pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence ſoever, does, as I have ſaid already, imply a diſlike, and does create an alienation of affection in the parties ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parating from one another, and therefore ſince a quarrel is much more eaſily fomented than begun; ſince it is hard in many caſes for the beſt tempers to be reconciled to one another, but very eaſie by new provocations to add new fewel to the fire of diſcord, till it grow maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs without any hopes of quenching, therefore no ſuch Separation ought ever to be made without neceſſary cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; and ſuch as make Communion in its own nature un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull, becauſe all other pretences are infinite, and at that rate there can be no end of Diſſention among men; eſpecially if we conſider farther, what is not perhaps ſo uſually regarded, or at leaſt not mentioned among the reaſons which prove a Separation unlawfull; men do not onely by this means divide from one another as to their religious concerns, but even in their temporal af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs they care not to deal or have to doe with one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and thus they trade, and marry, and converſe ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally with the men of their own way, and are almoſt to all intents and purpoſes as many diſtinct Societies as
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:53523:40"/> there are parties or factions in that unhappy Church whoſe misfortune it is to be ſo miſerably divided: the conſideration of which cannot chuſe but affright every man who has any regard either of his own peace, or to that of his Countrey, by preſenting him with a diſmal Scene of a Church divided and mangled into ſeveral diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreeing bodies, ſeparated in all reſpects from one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and as it were, drawn up in <hi>Battalia,</hi> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting onely the Signal of opportunity or advantage on any ſide to begin a bloudy encounter; which they that complain ſo heavily of Perſecution themſelves (when they have ſo little reaſon, and when they at the ſame time perſecute the Government and all that favour it with ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny and detraction, which is a very grievous ſort of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution) will certainly doe whenever it ſhall lie in their power. They having not onely given us a ſufficient ſpice of their temper in the late times, to teach us not to truſt them any more or any farther than needs muſt; but it is ſcarce longer ago than yeſterday, that the tender Conſciences were indulged ſo long till they grew too hard for the Government, and it is but too e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident, by their words and actions in that critical junc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that if they had gained their point, which was the ſubverſion of the preſent eſtabliſhment diſguiſed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſpecious pretences of uniting Proteſtants, who can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be united by any thing but a publick Form and Ritual of Divine Service; they would ſoon have ſhewn us what opinion they have of their pretended <hi>Diana</hi> Toleration, a Goddeſs never worſhipt in the publick Temples, and a word that never ſounds pleaſantly, but to thoſe that want the thing.</p>
            <p>So that an univerſal Toleration of all parties and opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons being manifeſtly proved to be naturally unlawfull, to be attended with infinite inconvenience and miſchief both to the publick and particular perſons, of which
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:53523:40"/> the body politick it ſelf is made up, as the whole is but an aggregate of ſeveral parts conſidered as one, and ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med up together, there remains now nothing farther to be conſidered under the topick of conceſſion, but that either we alter ſome ceremonies which have affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded matter or pretence of ſcruple for others in their ſtead, or that we do totally aboliſh whatever is excepted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, without any ſupplement or reparation: For the firſt of theſe, it is granted by ſuch as ſhall deſire it, that an impoſition in the general is lawfull, otherwiſe it would be ridiculous to talk of ſubſtituting other Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies in the ſtead of thoſe that are aboliſh'd, when the very ſubſtitution it ſelf is made an exception againſt them, it behoves thoſe perſons therefore who are deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of ſuch an alteration, ſince by the deſire it ſelf they do imply an acknowledgment, that a ſubſtitution, that is, a new impoſition may lawfully be made, and by conſequence that an impoſition in the general conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered is not unlawfull; I ſay, it concerns them to ſhew ſome particular reaſon, beſides the impoſition, of their diſlike of the Ceremonies which are already in uſe; for otherwiſe if we muſt alter them for no reaſon, we can have no certainty that this innovating humour will ever have an end, neither is it poſſible to make any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conſtruction of it, but that it proceeds out of a deſign to give an endleſs diſturbance to the publick peace, notwithſtanding it pretends to eſtabliſh and ſecure it. And as for thoſe, in the ſecond place, that are for abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing without a reparation, the caſe will be the ſame again; for either they are againſt thoſe Ceremonies, which they would have aboliſhed, merely for that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon becauſe they are impoſed, and then it is manifeſt they ought not to be heard, becauſe this, like <hi>Sampſon,</hi> with an honeſt perhaps, but yet a blind fury, and a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken zeal pulls up the very Pillars of Government from
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:53523:41"/> their natural baſis, and deſtroys the onely expedient un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Heaven of publick ſafety, ſecurity and peace; it makes the very worſhip of God it ſelf precarious and uncertain, and expoſes it at every turn to the deſign of Knaves, the deſtructive zeal of Madmen and Enthuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſts, the libertiniſm of Epicures and voluptuary perſons, to the ſcorn of Atheiſts, and the contempt of all wiſe, conſiderate and ſober men; there muſt therefore ſtill be another reaſon aſſigned why the Ceremonies that are boggled at ſhould be aboliſhed, and thoſe reaſons can be none but one of thoſe three that have been mentioned already, either they are too cumberſome by reaſon of their number, or they are ſuperſtitious in their uſe, or they are idolatrous in their direction.</p>
            <p>The firſt of theſe particulars hath been already con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered; and as to the ſecond, a Ceremony may be ſaid to be ſuperſtitiouſly uſed, when we aſcribe to it ſome Phyſical virtue or efficacy, or ſome ſupernatural effect which it hath not, or when we ſay that by or together with it, grace is conferred, as in the two Sacraments of Baptiſm and the Lord's Supper; but we do not affirm this of any of our Ceremonies, and our Church hath expreſly declared that ſhe intends nothing by them but onely peace, and decency, and edification; and for the uſe of the Croſs in Baptiſm, which is the great thing ſcrupled under this head of Superſtition, ſhe does expreſly declare that it doth not at all belong to the Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of it, that the Baptiſm is compleat without and before it, that it is onely a declarative rite of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons being liſted under Chriſt's Banner, of our being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated to his ſervice, who for our ſakes underwent ſo painfull and ſo ignominious a death, of our not being aſhamed of that Croſs which the Son of God himſelf underwent, and of our willingneſs, if occaſion be, to take up our Croſs and follow him through much
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:53523:41"/> tribulation and ſufferings into the glory of the Father. So that here there are but two things to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, either this Rite is unlawfull becauſe it hath been ſuperſtitiouſly abuſed by thoſe in the Romiſh Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and then upon the ſame account kneeling at our Prayers will be unlawfull, becauſe the Papiſts kneel to the hoſt, which yet, I preſume, none of the Diſſenters will be ſo hardy to ſay; or elſe, ſecondly, it will be ſaid, as ſome of them do, that it is therefore unlawfull becauſe it is a Ceremony of a ſymbolical or ſignificative nature, which is very ſtrange, as if a Ceremony could be unlawfull, onely for that reaſon, becauſe it tends to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dification, as it is the nature of a ſignificant Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to do. And here indeed is a great and common miſtake concerning indifferent things, as we do uſually, but falſely call them; for though we do not ſay, that any one Ceremony hath any ſuperſtitious efficacy or virtue in it, or that it can never upon any conſideration be changed or omitted, or that it is of abſolute neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in order to ſalvation, yet this muſt be confeſſed at the laſt, that many things are not ſo indifferent, as they are uſually eſteemed.</p>
            <p>It is very fit and conſequently a duty, that the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy ſhould go attired in black rather than in colours, that they ſhould wear long robes rather than ſhort, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhort hair than long, becauſe it will always be, that the latter of theſe will in the minds of all men create a ſenſe of levity, a diſpoſition to contempt, an opinion of luxury and eſſeminate ſoftneſs, whereas the former in the common interpretation of Mankind will always have a grave and a majeſtick appearance, they will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect authority, credit, and an opinion of ſobriety and ſtaidneſs upon him that wears them; and if the perſon be unlike what he appears, his habit which was deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed among other things for a mark of diſtinction, will be
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:53523:42"/> the greater and the more deſerved reproach to him. The Nonconformiſts themſelves are ſo ſenſible of this, that they themſelves wear black, for no good reaſon but what is ſymbolical, though they condemn that account of any thing we doe in us, and they wear long cloaks too, though Gowns and Caſſocks they have nothing to doe with, and therefore they do ſtill remain in a ſtate of ſuperſtition and uncleanneſs, onely for that reaſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are longer, that is, more grave, more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming, more authoritative, becauſe they preach better and perſwade more effectually than ſhort ones.</p>
            <p>The Surplice, a thing ſo much decryed and talked againſt by ſome, what is it to the Layety? or how come they ſo deeply to ſcruple it in others, who are not obliged to wear it themſelves? if they ſcruple it for no reaſon but onely becauſe they are not, that is, they will not be ſatisfied, a man can as little tell where ſuch an unaccountable ſcrupuloſity will end, as from whence it begins or upon what reaſon it is founded, when it is confeſſed to be founded upon no reaſon at all, beſides that it is intolerable, that they that talk ſo much of liberty themſelves, ſhould not leave us at our liberty to act as our Oaths and as the Laws oblige us, when they can aſſign no reaſon why we ſhould not, and when the diſpute is about a matter in which they are not perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally concerned: if there be any reaſon why it is ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled it is onely becauſe it is a ſymbolical thing which hath been already anſwered, beſides that it ſtands per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly upon the ſame bottom with their own putting on clean cloaths and change of raiment on a Sunday, which that that day of the week is choſe above all the reſt to doe it in, it muſt be confeſſed to be done upon a reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious account and a ſymbolical reaſon, out of reſpect to that day, and to intimate that purity and innocence of mind which is expected from them in the worſhip of
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:53523:42"/> God. For the Communion Tables being railed in, and ſeparated in that manner which it is from the reſt of the Church, it is declared in the Canons of 1640. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle 7. that it is onely to avoid that irreverence and profanation, which would otherwiſe bring a contempt upon all holy things, and upon the conſecrated Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments themſelves.</p>
            <p>It is rather neceſſary than otherwiſe that I ſhould be uncovered at Church, as being at that time more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the preſence of God, and that I ſhould kneel or ſtand rather than ſit at my Prayers, becauſe theſe are Natural poſtures of humility and reverence, and have been eſteemed ſo in all Ages and Nations, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as ſitting, or leaning, or lying along do betoken a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parative careleſneſs and diſregard of God and of his worſhip, and will without queſtion produce that bad effect upon the minds of men whereever they are put to practice; as on the contrary, a devout and ſubmiſſive geſture and deportment of our ſelves at the times and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>aces of religious worſhip is of real benefit and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to our ſelves, and is of good example to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and for the edification of all; which things are ſo plain and ſo undoubted a juſtification of all ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant Ceremonies, that I need ſay no more concerning them.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, there is no Ceremony in our Church, which is or is pretended to be Idolatrous in its direction, for as to the bowing towards the Altar or Communion-Table placed at the Eaſt end of the Church, it is left to every man's liberty by the Canons of 1640. to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have himſelf in that matter as he pleaſes, ſo that here is nothing impoſed, and yet becauſe this hath been for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly ſo highly cenſured, and perhaps with ſome more tolerable pretence, than any of the other exceptions that are made, I ſhould not uſe it, ſince I am not enjoined,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:53523:43"/> where it may give offence or be an occaſion of ſcandal to the weak, but in Cathedral or Collegiate Churches, where the Congregations uſually are better informed, there is no reaſon why it may not be done, for it is not pretended that we bow to any carved Image, or to the likeneſs of any living Creature whether in Heaven or Earth, which was the thing expreſly forbidden by the ſecond Commandment, that we worſhip the Railes or the Table it ſelf, or at any time the conſecrated Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon it, which is likewiſe included in the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of that Commandment, all which our Church does expreſly declare againſt, in as plain Language as words are capable of ſpeaking: And in the ſecond place it is to be conſidered, that the Iſraelites long before Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity was thought of, did always worſhip toward <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that is, towards a certain quarter of the Heavens without any the leaſt ſuſpicion of Idolatry, and that for ought appears, onely by humane inſtitution laſtly, I hope it will not be denied that God is in all times and places a very true and proper object of ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and that there is no quarter of the Heavens, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the ſymbolical reaſons upon which this practice depends, towards which we may not worſhip him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Idolatry.</p>
            <p>As for our kneeling at the Sacrament our Church hath ſufficiently declared her ſelf in this point, that ſhe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends no worſhip but to God onely, to God the Father, who ſent his onely begotten Son into the World to die for our ſins; to God the Son, who is then ſpiritually received, and dies afreſh for us in the merit, and virtue, and efficacy of his paſſion as often as we do worthily par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of thoſe holy myſteries, and to God the Holy Ghoſt, whoſe Grace is then implored and received by us.</p>
            <p>Becauſe the Papiſts worſhip their Breaden God, ſhall it therefore be unlawfull for us to kneel at our Prayers,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:53523:43"/> to behave our ſelves humbly in the preſence of the true and onely God, to acknowledge our offences, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent us of our ſins, and give thanks to God for his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, to pray that the Body and Bloud of our Lord <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt</hi> may preſerve our Body and Soul to everlaſting life, and to take that holy Sacrament to our unſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and eternal comfort, meekly kneeling upon our knees?</p>
            <p>But it would be infinite to ſay all that might be ſaid upon ſo copious a ſubject, in which I have all the way ſo plainly concurring with me, the voice of reaſon, of experience, and of the wiſeſt and beſt men of theſe and all times ever ſince the Reformation, therefore I ſhall ſumm up all, as I began, with the words of the Apoſtle, <hi>Let all things be done decently and in order.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
